<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Regrowth Not Degrowth</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/39_regrowth/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/39_regrowth/</guid><description>Comments on a recent Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese podcast : “Degrowth and MMT” with Christopher Olk and Colleen Schneider . This is from a big Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese fan. They&amp;rsquo;ve got a great library of podcasts.
Regrowth is Based While I absolutely unconditionally love my RealProgressives colleagues, the Degrowth meme and language framing is incrediubly dumb. I say this even though Bill Mitchell uses it (ok, he&amp;rsquo;s not a genius).
Here were my comments on the youtube copy of the podcast (I refuse Facebook, so cannto comment on the original websites).</description></item><item><title>Kant Hegel MMM?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/38_kant_v_hegel_v_mmt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/38_kant_v_hegel_v_mmt/</guid><description>Life has been friggin&amp;rsquo; traumatic for me recently, so excuse the low rate of blog output. Today I&amp;rsquo;m noting down a few thoughts after listening to Grumbine&amp;rsquo;s recent guest, Carlos García Hernández, on a topic he names “Fiat Socialism” &amp;mdash; a bit of a Frankenstein phrase if you ask me, which is what I&amp;rsquo;ll begin with, before getting into more juicy bits.
Language Framing I might make this language framing section a new regular feature of all my posts.</description></item><item><title>USA Holds Back</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/37_usa_holdingback/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/37_usa_holdingback/</guid><description>On the MMT MacroTrader livestream I often enjoy politely shocking a few friends by saying how much I love Americans. This does not extend to their government or organizations, particularly not the parasitic financial sector (the latter can just go away with no damage to the economy, with the exception of banks that are permitted to asses credit risk and run the payments layer). I love their land and their people.</description></item><item><title>Bondage and Discipline</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/25_discipline/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/25_discipline/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve written a few basic books on MMT questions and nuances, for the average reader, they&amp;rsquo;re not technical. But in this article I wanted to mention some things outside my area of expertise.
These can be important in some MMT activist activities, mainly when you run across some experts who know more than you. The trouble occurs when they do not know much about MMT, and have formed half-baked ideas about MMT.</description></item><item><title>SocMed Peer Reviews</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/36_socmedreviews/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/36_socmedreviews/</guid><description>Today&amp;rsquo;s blog title is a play on social science academia. What I&amp;rsquo;m really going to do is indulge in some reviews of a bit of Twitter banter. Unfortunately for the sake of time and limited resources (MMT joke, but serious) I&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to stick to giving some hot takes, but here at least I get to write more at length than in a tweet.
I do have a serious purpose though.</description></item><item><title>Is Tax Hygiene?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/35_taxhygiene/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/35_taxhygiene/</guid><description>Been reading the essays in Modern Monetary Theory: Key Insights, Leading Thinkers and so might make a few comments over the next weeks.
Overall The book is too boring. A lot of excess verbiage. But no matter, all the essays are worth reading, just some are real snoozers though.
Also, f$\ast\ast$k! MMT is sooo UK centric man! Can&amp;rsquo;t f$\ast\ast$ing apply anywhere else, oh&amp;hellip; maybe in the EU? ;-)
Is Tax a Hygiene factor?</description></item><item><title>MMT N00bs</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/34_mmtnoobs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/34_mmtnoobs/</guid><description>Today just some speech bullet points for people who may find they&amp;rsquo;re the &amp;ldquo;MMT expert in the room&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; meaning just an ordinary person who happens to know about MMT. These are the sorts of things you might want to have tattooed across your arms.
Caveats In polite discourse I do not recommend using my language of &amp;ldquo;Welfare Dorks&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;UBI Dorks&amp;rdquo; so please substitute appropriate terminology. Ōhanga Pai has elements of an MMT activist manifesto, so I allow myself such playful and provocative language.</description></item><item><title>Blockchain Redundacle</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/33_blockchainredundacle/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/33_blockchainredundacle/</guid><description>The book “Blockchain Radicals” by Joshua Dávali promised up-front to give lefties or &amp;ldquo;revolutionaries&amp;rdquo; some insights into the way tech ools could promote social system and political change.
Since the modern scam grift/ponzi of all time, cryptocurrency, is a loony-toons libertarian project, I have no good reason to read Dávila&amp;rsquo;s book. But it was recommended by MMT aware writer Brett Scott, so I figured I should give Dávila some slack. This is my review.</description></item><item><title>Talk with Warren Mosler - II</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/32_warrenmosler2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/32_warrenmosler2/</guid><description>Besides chatting about physics, the other reason Warren called me was to help me reply to @paddymccoll on twitter who asked me about constraints on banks during the Bretton-Woods era.
Now, I am no expert on Bretton-Woods, but had talked with Steven Grumbine on the podcast Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese about foreign exchange constraints and things like BRICS currency, and all that. That was only because Steve could not get Bill Mitchell or another actual expert on the phone that week.</description></item><item><title>Talk with Warren Mosler - I</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/31_warrenmosler1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/31_warrenmosler1/</guid><description>If we are going to create chatMMT for fun, we are going to need a decent corpus of writing from Warren Mosler. You can&amp;rsquo;t easily get the snappy one-liners otherwise.
A lot of the cool stuff from Mosler is in youtube interviews, so some audio-to-text transcribing efforts are needed? Unpaid internships anyone? (Excuse the crassness! Couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself.) At least Google tensorflow tools can do most of the work for us these days.</description></item><item><title>Cyberpunked</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/30_cyberpunked/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/30_cyberpunked/</guid><description>Some lighter material today. I want to pump the youtuber Quinn’s Ideas who is a wonderful creator of scifi discourse content. I realize it is pretty hilarious that my blog which no one seems to read is desiring to pump a youtuber who needs no pumping (550K+ views not uncommon). But&amp;hellip; you know&amp;hellip; 500K people is a sniff of the number of eyeballs that should be watching decent indie content. If I can get just two people to subscribe to Quinn’s Ideas my work will be done for today.</description></item><item><title>UBInterested</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/29_ubinterested/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/29_ubinterested/</guid><description>Recently &amp;ldquo;friendlies&amp;rdquo; were hosting UBI shills, stabbing us in the back and twisting the knife, so I had to write to defend MMT.
I am so bitter about this I cannot name names, because that would imply friendly banter. I have to attack the ideas. There is nothing friendly about UBI, the UBI is a direct frontal attack on the working class. I have to fight back for workers.
When I name names, like Jason Hickel, Steve Keen, or Michael Hudson, or Paul Krugman, or Richard Wolff, and have something against their ideas to say, I&amp;rsquo;m always doing it in a good faith friendly way.</description></item><item><title>Mushrooms and University</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/28_mushrooms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/28_mushrooms/</guid><description>A few comments today on medicinal psilocybin use and research. But the university topic will go further, because we read in last weeks New Zealand capital city last surviving newspaper, The Dominion Post, that universities are being starved of funding, may need to fire thousands of staff, and cut back research. Thousands of staff is enormous for a small nation like New Zealand, not small fries.
Thanks to my good friend, you know who you are, for prompting me to post this one.</description></item><item><title>Big Price Smoothies</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/24_irsmoothie/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/24_irsmoothie/</guid><description>Internet friend Derek McDaniel posted some interesting stuff on Medium worth writing about. I&amp;rsquo;ll use it as an entry into some wider issues of a continued massive need for MMT awareness. Right?&amp;hellip; as if we don&amp;rsquo;t all know this need! What am I doing here? Trying to activate activated activists?
If &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rdquo; are the Government &amp;hellip; or a monopoly currency issuer, driving demand for your currency with coercive tax liabilities or similar means.</description></item><item><title>Justice and Knowing</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/27_justiceandknowing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/27_justiceandknowing/</guid><description>A few notes on the flurry of news media on AI technology and fears of new AI monopoly owners held by tech giants, or the same powers open source released for rogue actors and rogue states to exploit. Some of this commentary is good, some terrible.
The biggest tragedy is all the politicians and commentariate screaming bloody murder about &amp;ldquo;jobs&amp;rdquo; being taken away. They are utterly ignorant and have zero comprehension of MMT.</description></item><item><title>Statistical Knowing</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/26_statsknowing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/26_statsknowing/</guid><description>More criss-crossing with my philosophy of mind between the physics (over at T4GU ). Although I try to keep the economics implications stuff here at Ōhanga Pai, and the physics stuff over at T4GU, today I will hedge on where my readers go and point them here. Today is a special blog where I will start to record my staking of positions on what the recent artificial intelligence LLM models can and cannot do.</description></item><item><title>Shadow Banking</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/23_shadow_banking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/23_shadow_banking/</guid><description>Short article for this chapter, and mainly some links. Shadow banking arises when people find a need for credit and cannot get it from a licenced bank. At least that&amp;rsquo;s the basic story.
Overview Synopsis: (a) There is no essential need for shadow banks. (b) Shadow banks nevertheless pop up because government licencers fail to adequately provision the private banks. (c) The basic provision needed is not cash, but full 100% deposit insurance.</description></item><item><title>Fear & Loathing in Los Vital</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/25_agi_fearandloathing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/25_agi_fearandloathing/</guid><description>Sometimes I criss-cross posts on philosophy of mind between the physics (over at T4GU ) and the Macroeconomics here at Ōhanga Pai. Lunchtime today I was watching a fresh episode of Machine Language Street Talk &amp;mdash; MLST does not directly help with the MMT DougBot project, but I consider it peripheral research that&amp;rsquo;s loosely justified (for the creative mind you see, I can&amp;rsquo;t just go full Copilot and chatGPT for MMT).</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Discount</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/22_discounting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/22_discounting/</guid><description>In recent Twitter discourse (or should that be childish spats?) a few MMT&amp;rsquo;ers are sniping at other MMT&amp;rsquo;ers on how to best conduct socail discoourse. To be clear, I don&amp;rsquo;t think there are major disagreements in MMT analysis, but the emphais on the politics varies form person to person.
Thus, we get wbmosler who emphasises how the US economy is on a mild boom or bull run, thanks to interest rate hikes.</description></item><item><title>Stuff Conservatives Want</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/24_conservatives/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/24_conservatives/</guid><description>Realistic timestamp on this post, since it&amp;rsquo;s a short one commenting on a short twitter to and fro.
I don&amp;rsquo;t mind the smell of conservatives, and have many as friends.
Previous chapter Back to Posts Next chapter Stuff Too Nasty for Twitter TOC AGI Fear &amp; Loathing</description></item><item><title>Stuff Too Nasty for Twitter</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/23_toonastytwit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/23_toonastytwit/</guid><description>Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been becoming more resigned to the fact posts to Mastodon, Diaspora and Twitter are more about cheering the gang rather than getting people to think of updating their brain-based Bayesian filter .${}^\ast$
With this in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to post a few things here that I feel would just make enemies on social media, more than friends. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s light-hearted, and just to let off steam. Putting these posts on the github is a minimal act of sharing for those who care for a laugh.</description></item><item><title>When to Discard the MMT Lens</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/22_mmtfornow/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/22_mmtfornow/</guid><description>In recent times (tackling libertarians and crypto shills on social media) it has become glaringly apparent in economics &amp;mdash; macroeconomics in particular &amp;mdash; there is a massive culture of hostility to science. However, it is subtle, so worth writing about today.
When Science is Unscientific No macroeconomists aim to be unscientific, at least I think not. They do not intend to be hostile to science.
Yet anyone can claim they are &amp;ldquo;being scientific&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; say by legitimately using data, or logic, or a model.</description></item><item><title>Macro Platonification</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/21_macro_platonification/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/21_macro_platonification/</guid><description>Over on my physics website for Topological 4-Geon Theory (T4GU) I recently wrote about platonism (healthy for thinking) versus platonification (deadly for thinking, and for general living). I think that reference sentence just gave you a summary, so no need to feel compelled to read it, it is however background to this current blog post.
(BTW: I have more to write about the last topic, the Output Chasm , but it is a heavy topic, so took a break from it.</description></item><item><title>The Output Chasm</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/20_outputchasm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/20_outputchasm/</guid><description>Last post I wrote about the way the euroland is ponzi, which came from Warren Mosler at the MMT Fiscal Sustainability Conference 2010 , but that also led me to Bill Mitchell&amp;#39;s incredibly powerful statements on the massive costs of unemployment. The latter is what I want to focus more on today. I think it&amp;rsquo;s the single most important topic in macroeconomics. And second only in political economy to the issue of lasting world peace.</description></item><item><title>Why does all this matter?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</guid><description>Why does anything matter? I will always consider spiritual economics (which Ōhanga Pai is all about) as way above and beyond MMT. The thing about cold hard MMT is that it is open to the critique of &amp;ldquo;fetishizing work.&amp;rdquo; Although plenty of MMT scholars point out that&amp;rsquo;s a false bad-faith attack &amp;mdash; and I agree, most MMT economists and activists also share the same spiritual lens I do, they are just too sheepish to admit macroeconomics is more about justice than &amp;ldquo;distribution of output.</description></item><item><title>Euroland Is Ponzi</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/19_europonzi/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/19_europonzi/</guid><description>I was re-watching the MMT Fiscal Sustainability Conference 2010 (which has an interesting back-story) and found a lot of gems I&amp;rsquo;d forgotten. Bill Mitchell is hilarious, in a good way.
It was one of Mosler&amp;rsquo;s though that got me thinking.
At one point Warren says the eurozone member nations are effectively in a ponzi position. That&amp;rsquo;s using a particular definition of &amp;ldquo;ponzi&amp;rdquo;, which in this case was &amp;ldquo;having to get money from someone else&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Punked Plutocrat Power Plays</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/21_powerplays/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/21_powerplays/</guid><description>The Hard Problem of MMT It&amp;rsquo;s about time I start writing more about the Hard Problem of MMT. This is the problem of getting nations that have MMT currency systems to actually (a) acknowledge this, and (b) use this knowledge to implement the MMT Base Case, meaning,
Permanent Zero Interest Rate Policy National Job Guarantee Pension Payments Made When Due (scrap the phony Trust Funds) Narrow Banking proposals It goes without saying that anyone dimly aware of MMT will run this base case, if in power.</description></item><item><title>MMArt Critics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_mmtreviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_mmtreviews/</guid><description>Following on from the Questions chapter I wrote last week &amp;ldquo;MMT and the Periphery &amp;rdquo; commentary, I thought it might be useful to critically review the defences of MMT, from a hard core MMT perspective (that&amp;rsquo;s me). At least I think I am hard core. As in what Buttercup said to Bubbles . What I&amp;rsquo;d mean by that is taking a view that the Mosler MMT Base Case is in fact realizable in the real world.</description></item><item><title>Quantopian Series Notes</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</guid><description>A few highlights from the Quantopian Series worth remembering for teaching. these will start off unordered, but after I write a half dozen or so I will try to impose some loose pedagogical order. (That just means the links will change, ok. So if referencing use the TOC and search box instead.)
p-value Hacking Ref: Quantopian Lecture Series: p-Hacking and Multiple Comparisons Bias .
Terminology False positive &amp;mdash; a test indicates presence of an effect when in reality an oracle would say there is no effect.</description></item><item><title>MT-2 - Flow of Funds</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</guid><description>The second in the planned series on Macro Trading MMT (MT for short.)
Sectoral Balances for Trading Alan Longbon wrote an interesting article on SeekingAlpha which outlined his investment strategy, which is pretty simple and highly MMT informed.
&amp;ldquo;My investment approach is very simple. I find countries with the highest and strongest macro-fiscal flows and low levels of private debt and invest in them using country ETFs and contract for difference (CFDs)I use functional finance and sectoral flow analysis of the national accounts of the nations I invest in.</description></item><item><title>Machines Can't Think to Work</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_machinescandothework/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_machinescandothework/</guid><description>I get a few AI topic recommendations on social media these days, more frequently than a year ago, probably because I&amp;rsquo;m working with Douglas Macro Trader on neural net systems for predicting financial indices. Douglas and I have diverging views on the broader technology of so-called &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; (if it is true intelligence it is not artificial in my view).
I could write this article on my T4GU blog too, but since there is some overlap with the macroeconomics I thought it might be of interest to readers of Ōhanga Pai.</description></item><item><title>True Populist</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_true_populism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_true_populism/</guid><description>Anyone enjoy the first season of True Detective ? The &amp;ldquo;true detectives&amp;rdquo;, Rust and Marty, were very flawed people, but were driven by an unshakeable desire to see justice done &amp;mdash; admittedly only on the &amp;ldquo;catch the bad guy&amp;rdquo; side it has to be said, not the &amp;ldquo;raise up the poor&amp;rdquo; side, but whatever. Griping entertainment with cinematic risk (à la Scorsese ).
This post I&amp;rsquo;m going to have a crack at writing about similar risk in politics.</description></item><item><title>Media Whores</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</guid><description>I furore broke out in the right-wing media space recently, with some right-wing guy named &amp;ldquo;Crowder&amp;rdquo; attacking a &amp;ldquo;Jewish last name&amp;rdquo; right-wing media host &amp;mdash; probably by the name of Shapiro I am guessing. Shapiro apparently was offering Crowder a $\$50$ million contract over 4 years, but which had payments reduced if YouTube banned Crowder or if Crowder lost advertisers.
So what apparently happened is Crowder goes on some rant explaining how the Jewish side of the right-wing media is in league with &amp;ldquo;Big tech&amp;rdquo; and is out to stiff humble young millionaires like Crowder from getting their natural rights to the ad funds and billionaire oligarchs who fund right-wing media.</description></item><item><title>Status is a Beyatch</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</guid><description>Interesting conversation Bill Mitchell had with a Japanese economics &amp;ldquo;professor&amp;rdquo; (professes to know some economics).
I made a few notes, not too many.
Japan Slips in GDP/Per Capita Ranking &amp;mdash; so what? The professor harped on a bit about how Japan had a &amp;ldquo;lost decade&amp;rdquo;. Bill explained well that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see in Japan any real loss of output. Their population growth is stagnant, so their GDP growth rate will not be anything near to say Australia which has a faster growing population.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec3-4</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-3 Money is Still Not Gold Just wanted to make a note that in this lecture it finally makes sense why Mehrling is obsessed with gold.
It is because he has a strong history buff spirit about him.
It is really the first time in the MOOC series when gold becomes important.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-5</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-2 Money is Not Gold Mehrling thinks gold is money. This is nuts. He is terribly wrong, since a speck of gold dust is not a promise to redeem, nor a claim on anything.
Of course you can argue semantics: &amp;ldquo;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m defining gold dust as a &amp;lsquo;money thing&amp;rsquo; so suck it!</description></item><item><title>The Debt Pyramid or Stack</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</guid><description>It is very painful listening to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking.
Today the pain concerns the so-called money pyramid.
Money is Credit &amp;mdash; there is no pyramid&amp;hellip; Also all money is debt because credit is a promise to be redeemed, so is the debt of the issuer.
All money is an IOU of the issuer, the problem is getting others to accept it. However, a &amp;ldquo;money thing&amp;rdquo; (an IOU) is as good as gold if the issuer always backs up their promise to redeem.</description></item><item><title>Source of Surplus Value</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</guid><description>Even in Marx&amp;rsquo;s day &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; in social and relative utility terms, or any subjective terms that emerges in a society, was measured using the state&amp;rsquo;s unit of account (dollars, pounds, marks, yuan, yen, pesos, &amp;amp;c.)
So when some economist talks about theories of surplus value they often reduce to nominal terms (the state currency unit) not real terms (energy and material). But this is fine. As long as you know when it is appropriate to translate between real and nominal terms.</description></item><item><title>Proof of X</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</guid><description>In casual talks with Douglas MMT Trader questions about what constitutes a &amp;ldquo;proof of MMT&amp;rdquo; or a disproof arose.
New Zealand is an MMT Economy We already know, from the Banking Acts and Public Finance Acts that New Zealand is an MMT monetary economy.
Just thought I&amp;rsquo;d mention this upfront. Although the legal statutes only prove half the case. We&amp;rsquo;d also need the accounting rules in the software and public accounts to obey the sectoral balance identities.</description></item><item><title>Finance Politics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</guid><description>Itching for a scrap with something that can&amp;rsquo;t fight back, here I am going to combat some of Daniel Neilson&amp;rsquo;s substack posts (Soon Parted ). Not because I disagree, but because I find Daniel&amp;rsquo;s blog informative, but lacking an MMT lens. But he gets a lot right, and is a student of Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s, so he understands balance sheets and whatnot. So with Daniel Nielson we are not dealing with some unhinged libertarian or Austrian School fantasist.</description></item><item><title>Problems with 'Sovereignty' in the Periphery Nations</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/20_peripherynations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/20_peripherynations/</guid><description>Some fresh MMT education material starts today. I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting to the Blog recently more regularly, since starting the DougBot Project , and as part of that research effort the opportunity to pose some questions to the founder of MMT (in the modern 20th century form, as opposed to the Sumerian form) arose.
To prepare for a chat with Sir Warren Mosler (you guys have Knighthoods yet in the USA?&amp;hellip; well, c&amp;rsquo;mon, keep up you laggards).</description></item><item><title>Semantics of MMT</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</guid><description>One good thing about joining Douglas the MMT Trader is that I get exposed now to trolls and critics who want to debunk MMT. This might be fodder for several posts, so this is a Part-1. I am not going to launch into esoteric philosophy and money crankery, so don&amp;rsquo;t be scared. My approach is more mathematical. In the sciences, and let&amp;rsquo;s be generous and call macroeconomics a social science (there is theory and empirical data to test it, just not always conclusively), so we can formulate definitions, and theorems using the definitions, and then test them.</description></item><item><title>Accelerators and Repellers -1</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</guid><description>This is one in possibly a series of posts for the general audience on some of the dynamical systems ideas underlying macroeconomics. Our focus is on macro and mesoeconomics. So we are not interested in particular stock prices, or even sectors, we are interested in the main aggregated market indices (in the USA the SPX, NASDAQ and whatever). This is partly pragmatic. If you liken the economic system to the weather and climate, the climate is very predictable (highly macro) the weather is not (too micro).</description></item><item><title>Capitalism as It Exists</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</guid><description>Capitalism as Marx conceived it was a fiction. It was important because people believed it to be a reality (and well before Marx). When people act as if it is real then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.
MMT is a reality that people believe is a fiction. It is important because when people act as if MMT is a fiction then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-2</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</guid><description>I will be writing the odd blog post over the next month commenting on highlights from Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking - online from INET .
Today it&amp;rsquo;s a comment on when Mehrling starts out by alerting his students that he is going to talk about the ECB &amp;ldquo;as if&amp;rdquo; it were a private entity, and then only in later lectures talk about money as a creation of the state.</description></item><item><title>The Money Veils</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</guid><description>There are several veils surrounding money, some theoretical and philosophical, some practical and real. I started writing this essay after a friend (Douglas the MMT Trader ) suggested I listen to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s lectures on money and banking, which cover as reading material the collected works of Allyn Young.
After only a short browse through Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s book on the collected works of Allyn Young I discovered a few interesting things related to MMT that I thought worth blogging about.</description></item><item><title>Neural Net Predictors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</guid><description>I plan to be teaming up with my new friend Douglas over at MMT Macro Trader. We hope to be publishing research on use of convolutional neural net LSTM algorithms for predicting forward returns on the SPX.
Macro Finance I am doing this to further MMT education and research relevant to &amp;ldquo;very macro&amp;rdquo; stock market index fund data. The idea is that even though finance bros hate MMT, they cannot ignore MMT if the knowledge of the relevance of fiscal flows and sectoral balances gives them a superior prediction algorithm,</description></item><item><title>First content live</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</guid><description>After years of dithering and pussy footing around about where to publish my economic justice writing, I settled on this github repository&amp;hellip; because&amp;hellip; free-libre nerd.
I&amp;rsquo;m not out to build a following or anything like that, but just want activist-geeks (a non-vanishing class of people) to have some decent software to use that won&amp;rsquo;t be a perennial pain-in-the you-know-what for GNU+Linux users to install (last version of Minsky would not build from tarball nor run even when installed successfully from the Debian repo &amp;mdash; I think ProfKeen and hpcoder have achieved code bloat).</description></item><item><title>Macro Trading 1 - Intro</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</guid><description>Macro trading is something I&amp;rsquo;ve only recently looked into, not as a trader, but as an academic seeking more real world experience. Macro trading models can benefit from MMT, but do not really use a bare Keen&amp;ndash;Minksy model because of the need to model markets, which are sub-macro. So I place macro trading models in a category of mesoscopic MMT analysis.
The MMT Macro Trader Paradigm Douglas over at Doug - MMT Macro Trader does a terrific job of using Bayesian models and MMT fiscal flow analysis to get very, very good 30 day predictions for the S&amp;amp;P forward market.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Overview</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</guid><description>Overview of the Projects Asset Exchange Models These are pretty simple models in the class of &amp;ldquo;econophysics &amp;rdquo;. They are agent-based models, and show the basic wealth distributions that occur generically given some rules for how entities (individuals or units like small firms) exchange assets.
These models are great for thinking about fair distribution policies, which at a government regulatory level means fiscal policy. The models show that highly unfair wealth distributions naturally occur even when asset exchanges are uniform and random.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/00_blog_intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/00_blog_intro/</guid><description>These are raw journal entries. An Ōhanga Pai hackers journal. For specific content articles in chapter format see Philosophy or Empirical sections.
We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few projects on-the-go.
Asset exchange models (Drăgulescu&amp;ndash;Ispolatov&amp;ndash;Yakovenko models) Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin models in python (pymsky project) Job Guarantee models in the Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin framework. Econometric analysis of the central bank interest rate policy &amp;mdash; are interest rate hikes inflationary in the short run? (Interest&amp;ndash;income and forward pricing channels overwhelm the propensity to save/borrow discriminants).</description></item><item><title>Full Employment and Stability</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/7_fullemployment_and_pricestability/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/7_fullemployment_and_pricestability/</guid><description>A classic paper today. Mandatory MMT reading.
Warren Mosler&amp;rsquo;s 1997 is a little bit of MMT gold in a highly readable nugget of 17 pages. I recommend the journal article for the elegant typesetting, for educational fair use contact me and I can send you an electronic copy. For the free public version you can go to the UMKC website here: Full Employment and Price Stability .
Take-aways from Fixed vs Floating Exchange Rates Mosler analyses two illustrative cases:</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/00_empirical_intro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/00_empirical_intro/</guid><description>This section is for discussions (in article form) of theory and empirical research development.
Contributors are welcome, but will need to submit through the Contact form or email. Your article needs to be technical, not philosophical, with ideally a code contribution to the github repository.
The philosophy and questions section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for the Ōhanga Pai community.</description></item><item><title>Pension Fund Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</guid><description>In this chapter we take a look at superannuation schemes, why they are useless today and maybe even harmful, and why they were at one time useful in the past.
Up-front, to avoid you going away immediately, I will say superannuation funds are not harmful if governments running the schemes do not use them to create mass unemployment. The trouble is they do! Yet it&amp;rsquo;s just a policy mistake, so can be corrected.</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</guid><description>This is one of the more contentious chapters. The MMT lens suggests the inflation rate is the interest rate, or at least a high enough interest rate will equal the inflation rate. But not all MMT informed economists would agree, and that is pretty much only because the econometric data analysis is inconclusive. However, we are working on analysis to show the MMT base case is correct under most &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; opening circumstances, which is that in normal times an upwards adjustment in the interest rate is inflationary, one-for-one.</description></item><item><title>Deficit Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</guid><description>There are two prevalent myths about government deficits.
(Myth 1.) Government deficits accumulate to government debt, which must be paid back in higher taxes. (Myth 2.) Government deficits are not stimulus, because increasing the money supply (which is what a net government deficit does) will just increase prices, if no taxes are raised, so the purchasing power of the extra dollars lowers to adjust to the status quo, and the net effect is just a temporary disruption in the market.</description></item><item><title>Inflation Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Inflation and the Reality Inflation is defined as a continual increase in the general price level. It is imprecisely measured by indicators like the CPI (consumer price index, a weighted index of prices of typical commodities for sale in the state currency units).
Does Government Net Spending Cause Inflation? If you think &amp;ldquo;yes,&amp;rdquo; then you have succumbed to the Quantity Theory of Money (QTM) myth.
Note that the QTM identity is an equation that expresses an identity, so it is not wrong.</description></item><item><title>Tax Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Taxation and the Reality The reality:
Currency issuers do not, and cannot logically, use tax return for their spending. Currency users like you and I do not use tax return for our spending either, because we have legal authority to impose taxes. Special currency users like provincial or municipal governments) do not need tax receipts for their funding either, but local currency-using governments that do not receive sufficient central government grant funds can be forced to impose taxes to get funds (numbers, scorepoints, in their bank accounts).</description></item><item><title>What is Money?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</guid><description>This post is foundational. I know it is not what leftie activists like to read straight up. Definitions about finance and economic systems are for nerds, right?
Wrong. We can point out several things both lefties and conservatives get horribly wrong for their own causes, even when their hearts are in the right place. Foremost among these is the tax payer funding myth. The trouble is, the requisite background to understanding why &amp;ldquo;tax payer funding&amp;rdquo; is a myth, involves an understanding of what money is, in essence, and in practice.</description></item><item><title>Basic MMT and Economic Justice</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</guid><description>For most of this whole course on MMT I am going to use the example of New Zealand, since many people claim MMT only applies to a country like the USA which enjoys a global reserve currency status. This would be false. MMT applies perfectly well to a small open economy like New Zealand. The currency is the NZD.
The Bare Minimum If you have a very sharp mind and keen intelligence you can almost derive answers to most of the basic questions concerning state currency monopoly systems (which would describe most monetary systems in all major countries today) using the principles in the following four subsections:</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai Q&A</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/00_questions_intro/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/00_questions_intro/</guid><description>This section Questions is for mostly philosophical discussions (in article form). Main topics include macroeconomics, economic justice, the Job Guarantee policy and fiscal versus monetary policy. For public banking (really just banking in general) I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn heavily upon the prior work of Warren Mosler, Randall Wray, and Eric Tymoigne.
For employment issues I draw on Mosler again, and Bill Mitchell &amp;amp; Pavlina Tcherneva . For popular macroeconomics discourse I rely upon Money on the Left and Stephanie Kelton @Market Watch.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/26_tradebackwards/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/26_tradebackwards/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/contact/</guid><description>See how to contact me.</description></item><item><title>Support by donating to Ōhanga-Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/donations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/donations/</guid><description>kofi donations</description></item></channel></rss>