<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>MMArt Critics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_mmtreviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_mmtreviews/</guid><description>Following on from the Questions chapter I wrote last week &amp;ldquo;MMT and the Periphery &amp;rdquo; commentary, I thought it might be useful to critically review the defences of MMT, from a hard core MMT perspective (that&amp;rsquo;s me). At least I think I am hard core. As in what Buttercup said to Bubbles . What I&amp;rsquo;d mean by that is taking a view that the Mosler MMT Base Case is in fact realizable in the real world.</description></item><item><title>Quantopian Series Notes</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</guid><description>A few highlights from the Quantopian Series worth remembering for teaching. these will start off unordered, but after I write a half dozen or so I will try to impose some loose pedagogical order. (That just means the links will change, ok. So if referencing use the TOC and search box instead.)
p-value Hacking Ref: Quantopian Lecture Series: p-Hacking and Multiple Comparisons Bias .
Terminology False positive &amp;mdash; a test indicates presence of an effect when in reality an oracle would say there is no effect.</description></item><item><title>MT-2 - Flow of Funds</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</guid><description>The second in the planned series on Macro Trading MMT (MT for short.)
Sectoral Balances for Trading Alan Longbon wrote an interesting article on SeekingAlpha which outlined his investment strategy, which is pretty simple and highly MMT informed.
&amp;ldquo;My investment approach is very simple. I find countries with the highest and strongest macro-fiscal flows and low levels of private debt and invest in them using country ETFs and contract for difference (CFDs)I use functional finance and sectoral flow analysis of the national accounts of the nations I invest in.</description></item><item><title>Machines Can't Think to Work</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_machinescandothework/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_machinescandothework/</guid><description>I get a few AI topic recommendations on social media these days, more frequently than a year ago, probably because I&amp;rsquo;m working with Douglas Macro Trader on neural net systems for predicting financial indices. Douglas and I have diverging views on the broader technology of so-called &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; (if it is true intelligence it is not artificial in my view).
I could write this article on my T4GU blog too, but since there is some overlap with the macroeconomics I thought it might be of interest to readers of Ōhanga Pai.</description></item><item><title>True Populist</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_true_populism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_true_populism/</guid><description>Anyone enjoy the first season of True Detective ? The &amp;ldquo;true detectives&amp;rdquo;, Rust and Marty, were very flawed people, but were driven by an unshakeable desire to see justice done &amp;mdash; admittedly only on the &amp;ldquo;catch the bad guy&amp;rdquo; side it has to be said, not the &amp;ldquo;raise up the poor&amp;rdquo; side, but whatever. Griping entertainment with cinematic risk (à la Scorsese ).
This post I&amp;rsquo;m going to have a crack at writing about similar risk in politics.</description></item><item><title>Media Whores</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</guid><description>I furore broke out in the right-wing media space recently, with some right-wing guy named &amp;ldquo;Crowder&amp;rdquo; attacking a &amp;ldquo;Jewish last name&amp;rdquo; right-wing media host &amp;mdash; probably by the name of Shapiro I am guessing. Shapiro apparently was offering Crowder a $\$50$ million contract over 4 years, but which had payments reduced if YouTube banned Crowder or if Crowder lost advertisers.
So what apparently happened is Crowder goes on some rant explaining how the Jewish side of the right-wing media is in league with &amp;ldquo;Big tech&amp;rdquo; and is out to stiff humble young millionaires like Crowder from getting their natural rights to the ad funds and billionaire oligarchs who fund right-wing media.</description></item><item><title>Status is a Beyatch</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</guid><description>Interesting conversation Bill Mitchell had with a Japanese economics &amp;ldquo;professor&amp;rdquo; (professes to know some economics).
I made a few notes, not too many.
Japan Slips in GDP/Per Capita Ranking &amp;mdash; so what? The professor harped on a bit about how Japan had a &amp;ldquo;lost decade&amp;rdquo;. Bill explained well that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see in Japan any real loss of output. Their population growth is stagnant, so their GDP growth rate will not be anything near to say Australia which has a faster growing population.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec3-4</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-3 Money is Still Not Gold Just wanted to make a note that in this lecture it finally makes sense why Mehrling is obsessed with gold.
It is because he has a strong history buff spirit about him.
It is really the first time in the MOOC series when gold becomes important.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-5</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-2 Money is Not Gold Mehrling thinks gold is money. This is nuts. He is terribly wrong, since a speck of gold dust is not a promise to redeem, nor a claim on anything.
Of course you can argue semantics: &amp;ldquo;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m defining gold dust as a &amp;lsquo;money thing&amp;rsquo; so suck it!</description></item><item><title>The Debt Pyramid or Stack</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</guid><description>It is very painful listening to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking.
Today the pain concerns the so-called money pyramid.
Money is Credit &amp;mdash; there is no pyramid&amp;hellip; Also all money is debt because credit is a promise to be redeemed, so is the debt of the issuer.
All money is an IOU of the issuer, the problem is getting others to accept it. However, a &amp;ldquo;money thing&amp;rdquo; (an IOU) is as good as gold if the issuer always backs up their promise to redeem.</description></item><item><title>Source of Surplus Value</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</guid><description>Even in Marx&amp;rsquo;s day &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; in social and relative utility terms, or any subjective terms that emerges in a society, was measured using the state&amp;rsquo;s unit of account (dollars, pounds, marks, yuan, yen, pesos, &amp;amp;c.)
So when some economist talks about theories of surplus value they often reduce to nominal terms (the state currency unit) not real terms (energy and material). But this is fine. As long as you know when it is appropriate to translate between real and nominal terms.</description></item><item><title>Proof of X</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</guid><description>In casual talks with Douglas MMT Trader questions about what constitutes a &amp;ldquo;proof of MMT&amp;rdquo; or a disproof arose.
New Zealand is an MMT Economy We already know, from the Banking Acts and Public Finance Acts that New Zealand is an MMT monetary economy.
Just thought I&amp;rsquo;d mention this upfront. Although the legal statutes only prove half the case. We&amp;rsquo;d also need the accounting rules in the software and public accounts to obey the sectoral balance identities.</description></item><item><title>Finance Politics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</guid><description>Itching for a scrap with something that can&amp;rsquo;t fight back, here I am going to combat some of Daniel Neilson&amp;rsquo;s substack posts (Soon Parted ). Not because I disagree, but because I find Daniel&amp;rsquo;s blog informative, but lacking an MMT lens. But he gets a lot right, and is a student of Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s, so he understands balance sheets and whatnot. So with Daniel Nielson we are not dealing with some unhinged libertarian or Austrian School fantasist.</description></item><item><title>Problems with 'Sovereignty' in the Periphery Nations</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/20_peripherynations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/20_peripherynations/</guid><description>Some fresh MMT education material starts today. I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting to the Blog recently more regularly, since starting the DougBot Project , and as part of that research effort the opportunity to pose some questions to the founder of MMT (in the modern 20th century form, as opposed to the Sumerian form) arose.
To prepare for a chat with Sir Warren Mosler (you guys have Knighthoods yet in the USA?&amp;hellip; well, c&amp;rsquo;mon, keep up you laggards).</description></item><item><title>Semantics of MMT</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</guid><description>One good thing about joining Douglas the MMT Trader is that I get exposed now to trolls and critics who want to debunk MMT. This might be fodder for several posts, so this is a Part-1. I am not going to launch into esoteric philosophy and money crankery, so don&amp;rsquo;t be scared. My approach is more mathematical. In the sciences, and let&amp;rsquo;s be generous and call macroeconomics a social science (there is theory and empirical data to test it, just not always conclusively), so we can formulate definitions, and theorems using the definitions, and then test them.</description></item><item><title>Accelerators and Repellers -1</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</guid><description>This is one in possibly a series of posts for the general audience on some of the dynamical systems ideas underlying macroeconomics. Our focus is on macro and mesoeconomics. So we are not interested in particular stock prices, or even sectors, we are interested in the main aggregated market indices (in the USA the SPX, NASDAQ and whatever). This is partly pragmatic. If you liken the economic system to the weather and climate, the climate is very predictable (highly macro) the weather is not (too micro).</description></item><item><title>Capitalism as It Exists</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</guid><description>Capitalism as Marx conceived it was a fiction. It was important because people believed it to be a reality (and well before Marx). When people act as if it is real then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.
MMT is a reality that people believe is a fiction. It is important because when people act as if MMT is a fiction then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-2</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</guid><description>I will be writing the odd blog post over the next month commenting on highlights from Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking - online from INET .
Today it&amp;rsquo;s a comment on when Mehrling starts out by alerting his students that he is going to talk about the ECB &amp;ldquo;as if&amp;rdquo; it were a private entity, and then only in later lectures talk about money as a creation of the state.</description></item><item><title>The Money Veils</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</guid><description>There are several veils surrounding money, some theoretical and philosophical, some practical and real. I started writing this essay after a friend (Douglas the MMT Trader ) suggested I listen to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s lectures on money and banking, which cover as reading material the collected works of Allyn Young.
After only a short browse through Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s book on the collected works of Allyn Young I discovered a few interesting things related to MMT that I thought worth blogging about.</description></item><item><title>Neural Net Predictors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</guid><description>I plan to be teaming up with my new friend Douglas over at MMT Macro Trader. We hope to be publishing research on use of convolutional neural net LSTM algorithms for predicting forward returns on the SPX.
Macro Finance I am doing this to further MMT education and research relevant to &amp;ldquo;very macro&amp;rdquo; stock market index fund data. The idea is that even though finance bros hate MMT, they cannot ignore MMT if the knowledge of the relevance of fiscal flows and sectoral balances gives them a superior prediction algorithm,</description></item><item><title>First content live</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</guid><description>After years of dithering and pussy footing around about where to publish my economic justice writing, I settled on this github repository&amp;hellip; because&amp;hellip; free-libre nerd.
I&amp;rsquo;m not out to build a following or anything like that, but just want activist-geeks (a non-vanishing class of people) to have some decent software to use that won&amp;rsquo;t be a perennial pain-in-the you-know-what for GNU+Linux users to install (last version of Minsky would not build from tarball nor run even when installed successfully from the Debian repo &amp;mdash; I think ProfKeen and hpcoder have achieved code bloat).</description></item><item><title>Why does all this matter?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</guid><description>Why does anything matter? I will always consider spiritual economics (which Ōhanga Pai is all about) as way above and beyond MMT. The thing about cold hard MMT is that it is open to the critique of &amp;ldquo;fetishizing work.&amp;rdquo; Although plenty of MMT scholars point out that&amp;rsquo;s a false bad-faith attack &amp;mdash; and I agree, most MMT economists and activists also share the same spiritual lens I do, they are just too sheepish to admit macroeconomics is more about justice than &amp;ldquo;distribution of output.</description></item><item><title>Macro Trading 1 - Intro</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</guid><description>Macro trading is something I&amp;rsquo;ve only recently looked into, not as a trader, but as an academic seeking more real world experience. Macro trading models can benefit from MMT, but do not really use a bare Keen&amp;ndash;Minksy model because of the need to model markets, which are sub-macro. So I place macro trading models in a category of mesoscopic MMT analysis.
The MMT Macro Trader Paradigm Douglas over at Doug - MMT Macro Trader does a terrific job of using Bayesian models and MMT fiscal flow analysis to get very, very good 30 day predictions for the S&amp;amp;P forward market.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Overview</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</guid><description>Overview of the Projects Asset Exchange Models These are pretty simple models in the class of &amp;ldquo;econophysics &amp;rdquo;. They are agent-based models, and show the basic wealth distributions that occur generically given some rules for how entities (individuals or units like small firms) exchange assets.
These models are great for thinking about fair distribution policies, which at a government regulatory level means fiscal policy. The models show that highly unfair wealth distributions naturally occur even when asset exchanges are uniform and random.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</guid><description>These are raw journal entries. An Ōhanga Pai hackers journal. For specific content articles in chapter format see Philosophy or Empirical sections.
We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few projects on-the-go.
Asset exchange models (Drăgulescu&amp;ndash;Ispolatov&amp;ndash;Yakovenko models) Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin models in python (pymsky project) Job Guarantee models in the Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin framework. Econometric analysis of the central bank interest rate policy &amp;mdash; are interest rate hikes inflationary in the short run? (Interest&amp;ndash;income and forward pricing channels overwhelm the propensity to save/borrow discriminants).</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/0_introduction_to_projects/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/0_introduction_to_projects/</guid><description>This section is for discussions (in article form) of theory and empirical research development.
Contributors are welcome, but will need to submit through the Contact form or email. Your article needs to be technical, not philosophical, with ideally a code contribution to the github repository.
The philosophy and questions section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for the Ōhanga Pai community.</description></item><item><title>Pension Fund Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</guid><description>In this chapter we take a look at superannuation schemes, why they are useless today and maybe even harmful, and why they were at one time useful in the past.
Up-front, to avoid you going away immediately, I will say superannuation funds are not harmful if governments running the schemes do not use them to create mass unemployment. The trouble is they do! Yet it&amp;rsquo;s just a policy mistake, so can be corrected.</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</guid><description>This is one of the more contentious chapters. The MMT lens suggests the inflation rate is the interest rate, or at least a high enough interest rate will equal the inflation rate. But not all MMT informed economists would agree, and that is pretty much only because the econometric data analysis is inconclusive. However, we are working on analysis to show the MMT base case is correct under most &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; opening circumstances, which is that in normal times an upwards adjustment in the interest rate is inflationary, one-for-one.</description></item><item><title>Deficit Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</guid><description>There are two prevalent myths about government deficits.
(Myth 1.) Government deficits accumulate to government debt, which must be paid back in higher taxes. (Myth 2.) Government deficits are not stimulus, because increasing the money supply (which is what a net government deficit does) will just increase prices, if no taxes are raised, so the purchasing power of the extra dollars lowers to adjust to the status quo, and the net effect is just a temporary disruption in the market.</description></item><item><title>Inflation Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Inflation and the Reality Inflation is defined as a continual increase in the general price level. It is imprecisely measured by indicators like the CPI (consumer price index, a weighted index of prices of typical commodities for sale in the state currency units).
Does Government Net Spending Cause Inflation? If you think &amp;ldquo;yes,&amp;rdquo; then you have succumbed to the Quantity Theory of Money (QTM) myth.
Note that the QTM identiy is an equation that expresses and identity, so it is not wrong.</description></item><item><title>Tax Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Taxation and the Reality The reality:
Currency issuers do not, and cannot logically, use tax return for their spending. Currency users (like provincial or municipal governments) do not need tax receipts for their funding either, but local currency-using governments that do not receive sufficient central government grant funds can be forced to impose taxes to get funds (numbers, scorepoints, in their bank accounts). The myth is that governments need to get their own currency off tax-payers before they can spend it!</description></item><item><title>What is Money?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</guid><description>This post is foundational. I know it is not what leftie activists like to read straight up. Definitions about finance and economic systems are for nerds, right?
Wrong. We can point out several things both lefties and conservatives get horribly wrong for their own causes, even when their hearts are in the right place. Foremost among these is the tax payer funding myth. The trouble is, the requisite background to understanding why &amp;ldquo;tax payer funding&amp;rdquo; is a myth, involves an understanding of what money is, in essence, and in practice.</description></item><item><title>Basic MMT and Economic Justice</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</guid><description>For most of this whole course on MMT I am going to use the example of New Zealand, since many people claim MMT only applies to a country like the USA which enjoys a global reserve currency status. This would be false. MMT applies perfectly well to a small open economy like New Zealand. The currency is the NZD.
The Bare Minimum If you have a very sharp mind and keen intelligence you can almost derive answers to most of the basic questions concerning state currency monopoly systems (which would describe most monetary systems in all major countries today) using the principles in the following four subsections:</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai Q&A</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/0_introduction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/0_introduction/</guid><description>This section Questions is for mostly philosophical discussions (in article form). Main topics include macroeconomics, economic justice, the Job Guarantee policy and fiscal versus monetary policy. For public banking (really just banking in general) I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn heavily upon the prior work of Warren Mosler, Randall Wray, and Eric Tymoigne.
For employment issues I draw on Mosler again, and Bill Mitchell &amp;amp; Pavlina Tcherneva . For popular macroeconomics discourse I rely upon Money on the Left and Stephanie Kelton @Market Watch.</description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/contact/</guid><description>See how to contact me.</description></item><item><title>Support by donating to Ōhanga-Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/donations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/donations/</guid><description>kofi donations</description></item></channel></rss>