<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai Q&A</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/000_questions_intro/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/000_questions_intro/</guid><description>This section Questions is for mostly philosophical discussions (in article form). Main topics include macroeconomics, economic justice, the Job Guarantee policy and fiscal versus monetary policy. For public banking (really just banking in general) I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn heavily upon the prior work of Warren Mosler, Randall Wray, and Eric Tymoigne.
For employment issues I draw on Mosler again, and Bill Mitchell &amp;amp; Pavlina Tcherneva . For popular macroeconomics discourse I rely upon Money on the Left and Stephanie Kelton @Market Watch.</description></item><item><title>What is Money?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/003_what_is_money/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/003_what_is_money/</guid><description>This post is foundational. I know it is not what leftie activists like to read straight up. Definitions about finance and economic systems are for nerds, right?
Wrong. We can point out several things both lefties and conservatives get horribly wrong for their own causes, even when their hearts are in the right place. Foremost among these is the tax payer funding myth. The trouble is, the requisite background to understanding why &amp;ldquo;tax payer funding&amp;rdquo; is a myth, involves an understanding of what money is, in essence, and in practice.</description></item><item><title>Tax Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/004_tax_myths/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/004_tax_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Taxation and the Reality The reality:
Currency issuers do not, and cannot logically, use tax return for their spending. Currency users like you and I do not use tax return for our spending either, because we do not have legal authority to impose taxes in the first place. Special currency users like provincial or municipal governments) do not need tax receipts for their funding either, but local currency-using branches of governments that do not receive sufficient central government grant funds can be forced to impose taxes to get funds (numbers, scorepoints, in their bank accounts).</description></item><item><title>Inflation Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/005_inflation_myths/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/005_inflation_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Inflation and the Reality Inflation is defined as a continual increase in the general price level. It is imprecisely measured by indicators like the CPI (consumer price index, a weighted index of prices of typical commodities for sale in the state currency units).
Does Government Net Spending Cause Inflation? If you think &amp;ldquo;yes,&amp;rdquo; then you have succumbed to the Quantity Theory of Money (QTM) myth.
Note that the QTM identity is an equation that expresses an identity, so it is not wrong.</description></item><item><title>Deficit Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/006_deficit_myths/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/006_deficit_myths/</guid><description>There are two prevalent myths about government deficits.
(Myth 1.) Government deficits accumulate to government debt, which must be paid back in higher taxes. (Myth 2.) Government deficits are not stimulus, because increasing the money supply (which is what a net government deficit does) will just increase prices, if no taxes are raised, so the purchasing power of the extra dollars lowers to adjust to the status quo, and the net effect is just a temporary disruption in the market.</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/007_interest_rate_myths/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/007_interest_rate_myths/</guid><description>This is one of the more contentious chapters. The MMT lens suggests the inflation rate is the interest rate, or at least a high enough interest rate will equal the inflation rate. But not all MMT informed economists would agree, and that is pretty much only because the econometric data analysis is inconclusive. However, we are working on analysis to show the MMT base case is correct under most &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; opening circumstances, which is that in normal times an upwards adjustment in the interest rate is inflationary, one-for-one.</description></item><item><title>Full Employment and Stability</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/008_fullemployment_and_pricestability/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/008_fullemployment_and_pricestability/</guid><description>A classic paper today. Mandatory MMT reading.
Warren Mosler&amp;rsquo;s 1997 is a little bit of MMT gold in a highly readable nugget of 17 pages. I recommend the journal article for the elegant typesetting, for educational fair use contact me and I can send you an electronic copy. For the free public version you can go to the UMKC website here: Full Employment and Price Stability .
Take-aways from Fixed vs Floating Exchange Rates Mosler analyses two illustrative cases:</description></item><item><title>Pension Fund Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/012_pension_funds/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/012_pension_funds/</guid><description>In this chapter we take a look at superannuation schemes, why they are useless today and maybe even harmful, and why they were at one time useful in the past.
Up-front, to avoid you going away immediately, I will say superannuation funds are not harmful if governments running the schemes do not use them to create mass unemployment. The trouble is they do! Yet it&amp;rsquo;s just a policy mistake, so can be corrected.</description></item><item><title>Problems with 'Sovereignty' in the Periphery Nations</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/020_peripherynations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/020_peripherynations/</guid><description>Some fresh MMT education material starts today. I&amp;rsquo;ve been posting to the Blog recently more regularly, since starting the DougBot Project , and as part of that research effort the opportunity to pose some questions to the founder of MMT (in the modern 20th century form, as opposed to the Sumerian form) arose.
To prepare for a chat with Sir Warren Mosler (you guys have Knighthoods yet in the USA?&amp;hellip; well, c&amp;rsquo;mon, keep up you laggards).</description></item><item><title>Punked Plutocrat Power Plays</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/021_powerplays/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/021_powerplays/</guid><description>The Hard Problem of MMT It&amp;rsquo;s about time I start writing more about the Hard Problem of MMT. This is the problem of getting nations that have MMT currency systems to actually (a) acknowledge this, and (b) use this knowledge to implement the MMT Base Case, meaning,
Permanent Zero Interest Rate Policy National Job Guarantee Pension Payments Made When Due (scrap the phony Trust Funds) Narrow Banking proposals It goes without saying that anyone dimly aware of MMT will run this base case, if in power.</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Discount</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/022_discounting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/022_discounting/</guid><description>In recent Twitter discourse (or should that be childish spats?) a few MMT&amp;rsquo;ers are sniping at other MMT&amp;rsquo;ers on how to best conduct social discourse. To be clear, I don&amp;rsquo;t think there are major disagreements in MMT analysis, but the emphasis on the politics varies form person to person.
Thus, we get wbmosler who emphasises how the US economy is on a mild boom or bull run, thanks to interest rate hikes.</description></item><item><title>Shadow Banking</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/023_shadow_banking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/023_shadow_banking/</guid><description>Short article for this chapter, and mainly some links. Shadow banking arises when people find a need for credit and cannot get it from a licenced bank. At least that&amp;rsquo;s the basic story.
Overview Synopsis: (a) There is no essential need for shadow banks. (b) Shadow banks nevertheless pop up because government licencers fail to adequately provision the private banks. (c) The basic provision needed is not cash, but full 100% deposit insurance.</description></item><item><title>Big Price Smoothies</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/024_irsmoothie/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/024_irsmoothie/</guid><description>Internet friend Derek McDaniel posted some interesting stuff on Medium worth writing about. I&amp;rsquo;ll use it as an entry into some wider issues of a continued massive need for MMT awareness. Right?&amp;hellip; as if we don&amp;rsquo;t all know this need! What am I doing here? Trying to activate activated activists?
If &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rdquo; are the Government &amp;hellip; or a monopoly currency issuer, driving demand for your currency with coercive tax liabilities or similar means.</description></item><item><title>Bondage and Discipline</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/025_discipline/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/025_discipline/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve written a few basic books on MMT questions and nuances, for the average reader, they&amp;rsquo;re not technical. But in this article I wanted to mention some things outside my area of expertise.
These can be important in some MMT activist activities, mainly when you run across some experts who know more than you. The trouble occurs when they do not know much about MMT, and have formed half-baked ideas about MMT.</description></item><item><title>Trade Backwards</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/026_tradebackwards/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/026_tradebackwards/</guid><description>I got interrupted, so never started this post.
But it was a reminder that mainstream econ, even most Post-Keynesians, have the trade story partly backwards.
Ideally a nation does not want to trade, except for what they cannot domestically produce.
Practically all nations want to trade because they cannot source all their needs domestically.
The purpose of trade is not to generate peaceful relations, but peaceful relations is a happy consequence or side-effect.</description></item><item><title>Without Government, Unemployment?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/027_without_government_no_unemployment/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/027_without_government_no_unemployment/</guid><description>There is this issue libertarian nut-cases and MMT&amp;rsquo;ers might agree upon in crudest form: without government there is no unemployment. But MMT has a very different perspective. We want a good government and we want full employment, and we can in fact have both. It is a political choice, not a whim of natural markets.
The (correct) MMT statement is,
With government there is unemployment by design, from inception, but also with government all the unemployment generated should (morally and optimally) be immediately eliminated.</description></item><item><title>Why does all this matter?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</guid><description>Why does anything matter? I will always consider spiritual economics (which Ōhanga Pai is all about) as way above and beyond MMT. The thing about cold hard MMT is that it is open to the critique of &amp;ldquo;fetishizing work.&amp;rdquo; Although plenty of MMT scholars point out that&amp;rsquo;s a false bad-faith attack &amp;mdash; and I agree, most MMT economists and activists also share the same spiritual lens I do, they are just too sheepish to admit macroeconomics is more about justice than &amp;ldquo;distribution of output.</description></item><item><title>Basic MMT and Economic Justice</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/001_basic_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/001_basic_ohangapai/</guid><description>For most of this whole course on MMT I am going to use the example of New Zealand, since many people claim MMT only applies to a country like the USA which enjoys a global reserve currency status. This would be false on both counts. MMT applies perfectly well to a small open economy like New Zealand. The currency is the NZD. The US dollar is not a global reserve currency, since the Bretton-Woods system was abandoned over 50 years ago.</description></item></channel></rss>