<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why does all this matter?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/100_why_does_it_matter/</guid><description>Why does anything matter? I will always consider spiritual economics (which Ōhanga Pai is all about) as way above and beyond MMT. The thing about cold hard MMT is that it is open to the critique of &amp;ldquo;fetishizing work.&amp;rdquo; Although plenty of MMT scholars point out that&amp;rsquo;s a false bad-faith attack &amp;mdash; and I agree, most MMT economists and activists also share the same spiritual lens I do, they are just too sheepish to admit macroeconomics is more about justice than &amp;ldquo;distribution of output.</description></item><item><title>Pension Fund Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/12_pension_funds/</guid><description>In this chapter we take a look at superannuation schemes, why they are useless today and maybe even harmful, and why they were at one time useful in the past.
Up-front, to avoid you going away immediately, I will say superannuation funds are not harmful if governments running the schemes do not use them to create mass unemployment. The trouble is they do! Yet it&amp;rsquo;s just a policy mistake, so can be corrected.</description></item><item><title>Interest Rate Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/6_interest_rate_myths/</guid><description>Next chapter (TBC) Previous chapter (Deficit Myths) Back to Questions TOC</description></item><item><title>Deficit Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/5_deficit_myths/</guid><description>There are two prevalent myths about government deficits.
(Myth 1.) Government deficits accumulate to government debt, which must be paid back in higher taxes. (Myth 2.) Government deficits are not stimulus, because increasing the money supply (which is what a net government deficit does) will just increase prices, if no taxes are raised, so the purchasing power of the extra dollars lowers to adjust to the status quo, and the net effect is just a temporary disruption in the market.</description></item><item><title>Inflation Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/4_inflation_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Inflation and the Reality Inflation is defined as a continual increase in the general price level. It is imprecisely measured by indicators like the CPI (consumer price index, a weighted index of prices of typical commodities for sale in the state currency units).
Does Government Net Spending Cause Inflation? If you think &amp;ldquo;yes,&amp;rdquo; then you have succumbed to the Quantity Theory of Money (QTM) myth.
The reality is that never in all recorded history have government deficits caused hyperinflations.</description></item><item><title>Tax Myths</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/3_tax_myths/</guid><description>Myths about Taxation and the Reality The reality:
Currency issuers do not, and cannot logically, use tax return for their spending. Currency users (like provincial or municipal governments) do not need tax receipts for their funding either, but local currency-using governments that do not receive sufficient central government grant funds can be forced to impose taxes to get funds (numbers, scorepoints, in their bank accounts). The myth is that governments need to get their own currency off tax-payers before they can spend it!</description></item><item><title>What is Money?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/2_what_is_money/</guid><description>This post is foundational. I know it is not what leftie activists like to read straight up. Definitions about finance and economic systems are for nerds, right?
Wrong. We can point out several things both lefties and conservatives get horribly wrong for their own causes, even when their hearts are in the right place. Foremost among these is the tax payer funding myth. The trouble is, the requisite background to understanding why &amp;ldquo;tax payer funding&amp;rdquo; is a myth, involves an understanding of what money is, in essence, and in practice.</description></item><item><title>Basic MMT and Economic Justice</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/1_basic_ohangapai/</guid><description>For most of this whole course on MMT I am going to use the example of New Zealand, since many people claim MMT only applies to a country like the USA which enjoys a global reserve currency status. This would be false. MMT applies perfectly well to a small open economy like New Zealand. The currency is the NZD.
The Bare Minimum If you have a very sharp mind and keen intelligence you can almost derive answers to most of the basic questions concerning state currency monopoly systems (which would describe most monetary systems in all major countries today) using the principles in the following four subsections:</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai Q&A</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/0_introduction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/questions/0_introduction/</guid><description>This section Questions is for mostly philosophical discussions (in article form). Main topics include macroeconomics, economic justice, the Job Guarantee policy and fiscal versus monetary policy. For public banking (really just banking in general) I&amp;rsquo;ve drawn heavily upon the prior work of Warren Mosler, Randall Wray, and Eric Tymoigne.
For employment issues I draw on Mosler again, and Bill Mitchell &amp;amp; Pavlina Tcherneva . For popular macroeconomics discourse I rely upon Money on the Left and Stephanie Kelton @Market Watch.</description></item></channel></rss>