<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Media Whores</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_media_whores/</guid><description>I furore broke out in the right-wing media space recently, with some right-wing guy named &amp;ldquo;Crowder&amp;rdquo; attacking a &amp;ldquo;Jewish last name&amp;rdquo; right-wing media host &amp;mdash; probably by the name of Shapiro I am guessing. Shapiro apparently was offering Crowder a $\$50$ million contract over 4 years, but which had payments reduced if YouTube banned Crowder or if Crowder lost advertisers.
So what apparently happened is Crowder goes on some rant explaining how the Jewish side of the right-wing media is in league with &amp;ldquo;Big tech&amp;rdquo; and is out to stiff humble young millionaires like Crowder from getting their natural rights to the ad funds and billionaire oligarchs who fund right-wing media.</description></item><item><title>Status is a Beyatch</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_status_bitches/</guid><description>Interesting conversation Bill Mitchell had with a Japanese economics &amp;ldquo;professor&amp;rdquo; (professes to know some economics).
I made a few notes, not too many.
Japan Slips in GDP/Per Capita Ranking &amp;mdash; so what? The professor harped on a bit about how Japan had a &amp;ldquo;lost decade&amp;rdquo;. Bill explained well that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see in Japan any real loss of output. Their population growth is stagnant, so their GDP growth rate will not be anything near to say Australia which has a faster growing population.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec3-4</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_mab_2_5_gold/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-3 Money is Still Not Gold Just wanted to make a note that in this lecture it finally makes sense why Mehrling is obsessed with gold.
It is because he has a strong history buff spirit about him.
It is really the first time in the MOOC series when gold becomes important.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-5</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-2 Money is Not Gold Mehrling thinks gold is money. This is nuts. He is terribly wrong, since a speck of gold dust is not a promise to redeem, nor a claim on anything.
Of course you can argue semantics: &amp;ldquo;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m defining gold dust as a &amp;lsquo;money thing&amp;rsquo; so suck it!</description></item><item><title>The Debt Pyramid or Stack</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_debt_pyramid/</guid><description>It is very painful listening to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking.
Today the pain concerns the so-called money pyramid.
Money is Credit &amp;mdash; there is no pyramid&amp;hellip; Also all money is debt because credit is a promise to be redeemed, so is the debt of the issuer.
All money is an IOU of the issuer, the problem is getting others to accept it. However, a &amp;ldquo;money thing&amp;rdquo; (an IOU) is as good as gold if the issuer always backs up their promise to redeem.</description></item><item><title>Source of Surplus Value</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_surplus_value/</guid><description>Even in Marx&amp;rsquo;s day &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; in social and relative utility terms, or any subjective terms that emerges in a society, was measured using the state&amp;rsquo;s unit of account (dollars, pounds, marks, yuan, yen, pesos, &amp;amp;c.)
So when some economist talks about theories of surplus value they often reduce to nominal terms (the state currency unit) not real terms (energy and material). But this is fine. As long as you know when it is appropriate to translate between real and nominal terms.</description></item><item><title>Proof of X</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_proof_of_x/</guid><description>In casual talks with Douglas MMT Trader questions about what constitutes a &amp;ldquo;proof of MMT&amp;rdquo; or a disproof arose.
New Zealand is an MMT Economy We already know, from the Banking Acts and Public Finance Acts that New Zealand is an MMT monetary economy.
Just thought I&amp;rsquo;d mention this upfront. Although the legal statutes only prove half the case. We&amp;rsquo;d also need the accounting rules in the software and public accounts to obey the sectoral balance identities.</description></item><item><title>Finance Politics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/9_finance_politics/</guid><description>Itching for a scrap with something that can&amp;rsquo;t fight back, here I am going to combat some of Daniel Neilson&amp;rsquo;s substack posts (Soon Parted ). Not because I disagree, but because I find Daniel&amp;rsquo;s blog informative, but lacking an MMT lens. But he gets a lot right, and is a student of Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s, so he understands balance sheets and whatnot. So with Daniel Nielson we are not dealing with some unhinged libertarian or Austrian School fantasist.</description></item><item><title>Semantics of MMT</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/8_mmt_semantics/</guid><description>One good thing about joining Douglas the MMT Trader is that I get exposed now to trolls and critics who want to debunk MMT. This might be fodder for several posts, so this is a Part-1. I am not going to launch into esoteric philosophy and money crankery, so don&amp;rsquo;t be scared. My approach is more mathematical. In the sciences, and let&amp;rsquo;s be generous and call macroeconomics a social science (there is theory and empirical data to test it, just not always conclusively), so we can formulate definitions, and theorems using the definitions, and then test them.</description></item><item><title>Accelerators and Repellers -1</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</guid><description>This is one in possibly a series of posts for the general audience on some of the dynamical systems ideas underlying macroeconomics. Our focus is on macro and mesoeconomics. So we are not interested in particular stock prices, or even sectors, we are interested in the main aggregated market indices (in the USA the SPX, NASDAQ and whatever). This is partly pragmatic. If you liken the economic system to the weather and climate, the climate is very predictable (highly macro) the weather is not (too micro).</description></item><item><title>Capitalism as It Exists</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</guid><description>Capitalism as Marx conceived it was a fiction. It was important because people believed it to be a reality (and well before Marx). When people act as if it is real then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.
MMT is a reality that people believe is a fiction. It is important because when people act as if MMT is a fiction then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-2</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</guid><description>I will be writing the odd blog post over the next month commenting on highlights from Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking - online from INET .
Today it&amp;rsquo;s a comment on when Mehrling starts out by alerting his students that he is going to talk about the ECB &amp;ldquo;as if&amp;rdquo; it were a private entity, and then only in later lectures talk about money as a creation of the state.</description></item><item><title>The Money Veils</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</guid><description>There are several veils surrounding money, some theoretical and philosophical, some practical and real. I started writing this essay after a friend (Douglas the MMT Trader ) suggested I listen to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s lectures on money and banking, which cover as reading material the collected works of Allyn Young.
After only a short browse through Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s book on the collected works of Allyn Young I discovered a few interesting things related to MMT that I thought worth blogging about.</description></item><item><title>Neural Net Predictors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</guid><description>I plan to be teaming up with my new friend Douglas over at MMT Macro Trader. We hope to be publishing research on use of convolutional neural net LSTM algorithms for predicting forward returns on the SPX.
Macro Finance I am doing this to further MMT education and research relevant to &amp;ldquo;very macro&amp;rdquo; stock market index fund data. The idea is that even though finance bros hate MMT, they cannot ignore MMT if the knowledge of the relevance of fiscal flows and sectoral balances gives them a superior prediction algorithm,</description></item><item><title>First content live</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</guid><description>After years of dithering and pussy footing around about where to publish my economic justice writing, I settled on this github repository&amp;hellip; because&amp;hellip; free-libre nerd.
I&amp;rsquo;m not out to build a following or anything like that, but just want activist-geeks (a non-vanishing class of people) to have some decent software to use that won&amp;rsquo;t be a perennial pain-in-the you-know-what for GNU+Linux users to install (last version of Minsky would not build from tarball nor run even when installed successfully from the Debian repo &amp;mdash; I think ProfKeen and hpcoder have achieved code bloat).</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</guid><description>These are raw journal entries. An Ōhanga Pai hackers journal. For specific content articles in chapter format see Philosophy or Empirical sections.
We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few projects on-the-go.
Asset exchange models (Drăgulescu&amp;ndash;Ispolatov&amp;ndash;Yakovenko models) Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin models in python (pymsky project) Job Guarantee models in the Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin framework. Econometric analysis of the central bank interest rate policy &amp;mdash; are interest rate hikes inflationary in the short run? (Interest&amp;ndash;income and forward pricing channels overwhelm the propensity to save/borrow discriminants).</description></item></channel></rss>