<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is a Cashless Society Good?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/7_accelerators_repellers/</guid><description>Over at Real Progressives (an awesome educational and activist group) they have a library of podcasts on macroeconomics and social issues relevant to our times, loads of politics and brilliant thinkers. One of them is Brett Scott (a South African, probably a Bok supporter, but we won&amp;rsquo;t hold that against him aye All Blacks fans). His wheelhouse is fintec (the horrors of it) and payments systems, particularly cash, and the War on Cash (for readers) or if you prefer watching talks, try here.</description></item><item><title>Capitalism as It Exists</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/5_capitalrealism/</guid><description>Capitalism as Marx conceived it was a fiction. It was important because people believed it to be a reality (and well before Marx). When people act as if it is real then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.
MMT is a reality that people believe is a fiction. It is important because when people act as if MMT is a fiction then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-2</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/4_mab_2_2_euroland/</guid><description>I will be writing the odd blog post over the next month commenting on highlights from Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking - online from INET Today it&amp;rsquo;s a comment on when Mehrling starts out by alerting his students that he is going to talk about the ECB &amp;ldquo;as if&amp;rdquo; it were a private entity, and then only in later lectures talk about money as a creation of the state.</description></item><item><title>The Money Veils</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/3_money_veils/</guid><description>There are several veils surrounding money, some theoretical and philosophical, some practical and real. I started writing this essay after a friend (Douglas the MMT Trader ) suggested I listen to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s lectures on money and banking, which cover as reading material the collected works of Allyn Young.
After only a short browse through Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s book on the collected works of Allyn Young I discovered a few interesting things related to MMT that I thought worth blogging about.</description></item><item><title>Neural Net Predictors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/2_neural_nets_pt1/</guid><description>I plan to be teaming up with my new friend Douglas over at MMT Macro Trader. We hope to be publishing research on use of convolutional neural net LSTM algorithms for predicting forward returns on the SPX.
Macro Finance I am doing this to further MMT education and research relevant to &amp;ldquo;very macro&amp;rdquo; stock market index fund data. The idea is that even though finance bros hate MMT, they cannot ignore MMT if the knowledge of the relevance of fiscal flows and sectoral balances gives them a superior prediction algorithm,</description></item><item><title>First content live</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/1_first_content/</guid><description>After years of dithering and pussy footing around about where to publish my economic justice writing, I settled on this github repository&amp;hellip; because&amp;hellip; free-libre nerd.
I&amp;rsquo;m not out to build a following or anything like that, but just want activist-geeks (a non-vanishing class of people) to have some decent software to use that won&amp;rsquo;t be a perennial pain-in-the you-know-what for GNU+Linux users to install (last version of Minsky would not build from tarball nor run even when installed successfully from the Debian repo &amp;mdash; I think ProfKeen and hpcoder have achieved code bloat).</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/0_intro_to_ohangapai/</guid><description>These are raw journal entries. An Ōhanga Pai hackers journal. For specific content articles in chapter format see Philosophy or Empirical sections.
We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few projects on-the-go.
Asset exchange models (Drăgulescu&amp;ndash;Ispolatov&amp;ndash;Yakovenko models) Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin models in python (pymsky project) Job Guarantee models in the Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin framework. Econometric analysis of the central bank interest rate policy &amp;mdash; are interest rate hikes inflationary in the short run? (Interest&amp;ndash;income and forward pricing channels overwhelm the propensity to save/borrow discriminants).</description></item></channel></rss>