<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/00_blog_intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/00_blog_intro/</guid><description>These are raw journal entries. An Ōhanga Pai hackers journal. For specific content articles in chapter format see Philosophy or Empirical sections.
We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few projects on-the-go.
Asset exchange models (Drăgulescu&amp;ndash;Ispolatov&amp;ndash;Yakovenko models) Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin models in python (pymsky project) Job Guarantee models in the Keen&amp;ndash;Goodwin framework. Econometric analysis of the central bank interest rate policy &amp;mdash; are interest rate hikes inflationary in the short run? (Interest&amp;ndash;income and forward pricing channels overwhelm the propensity to save/borrow discriminants).</description></item><item><title>Dithering No More</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/01_first_content/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/01_first_content/</guid><description>After years of dithering and pussy footing around about where to publish my economic justice writing, I settled on this github repository&amp;hellip; because&amp;hellip; free-libre nerd.
I&amp;rsquo;m not out to build a following or anything like that, but just want activist-geeks (a non-vanishing class of people) to have some decent software to use that won&amp;rsquo;t be a perennial pain-in-the you-know-what for GNU+Linux users to install (last version of Minsky would not build from tarball nor run even when installed successfully from the Debian repo &amp;mdash; I think ProfKeen and hpcoder have achieved code bloat).</description></item><item><title>Neural Net Predictors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/03_neural_nets_pt1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/03_neural_nets_pt1/</guid><description>I plan to be teaming up with my new friend Douglas over at MMT Macro Trader. We hope to be publishing research on use of convolutional neural net LSTM algorithms for predicting forward returns on the SPX.
Macro Finance I am doing this to further MMT education and research relevant to &amp;ldquo;very macro&amp;rdquo; stock market index fund data. The idea is that even though finance bros hate MMT, they cannot ignore MMT if the knowledge of the relevance of fiscal flows and sectoral balances gives them a superior prediction algorithm,</description></item><item><title>The Money Veils</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/04_money_veils/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/04_money_veils/</guid><description>There are several veils surrounding money, some theoretical and philosophical, some practical and real. I started writing this essay after a friend (Douglas the MMT Trader ) suggested I listen to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s lectures on money and banking, which cover as reading material the collected works of Allyn Young.
After only a short browse through Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s book on the collected works of Allyn Young I discovered a few interesting things related to MMT that I thought worth blogging about.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-2</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/05_mab_2_2_euroland/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/05_mab_2_2_euroland/</guid><description>I will be writing the odd blog post over the next month commenting on highlights from Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking - online from INET .
Today it&amp;rsquo;s a comment on when Mehrling starts out by alerting his students that he is going to talk about the ECB &amp;ldquo;as if&amp;rdquo; it were a private entity, and then only in later lectures talk about money as a creation of the state.</description></item><item><title>Capitalism as It Exists</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/06_capitalrealism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/06_capitalrealism/</guid><description>Capitalism as Marx conceived it was a fiction. It was important because people believed it to be a reality (and well before Marx). When people act as if it is real then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.
MMT is a reality that people believe is a fiction. It is important because when people act as if MMT is a fiction then we have a cause of great suffering for the many.</description></item><item><title>Accelerators and Repellers -1</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/08_accelerators_repellers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/08_accelerators_repellers/</guid><description>This is one in possibly a series of posts for the general audience on some of the dynamical systems ideas underlying macroeconomics. Our focus is on macro and mesoeconomics. So we are not interested in particular stock prices, or even sectors, we are interested in the main aggregated market indices (in the USA the SPX, NASDAQ and whatever). This is partly pragmatic. If you liken the economic system to the weather and climate, the climate is very predictable (highly macro) the weather is not (too micro).</description></item><item><title>Semantics of MMT</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/09_mmt_semantics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/09_mmt_semantics/</guid><description>One good thing about joining Douglas the MMT Trader is that I get exposed now to trolls and critics who want to debunk MMT. This might be fodder for several posts, so this is a Part-1. I am not going to launch into esoteric philosophy and money crankery, so don&amp;rsquo;t be scared. My approach is more mathematical. In the sciences, and let&amp;rsquo;s be generous and call macroeconomics a social science (there is theory and empirical data to test it, just not always conclusively), so we can formulate definitions, and theorems using the definitions, and then test them.</description></item><item><title>Finance Politics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_finance_politics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/10_finance_politics/</guid><description>Itching for a scrap with something that can&amp;rsquo;t fight back, here I am going to combat some of Daniel Neilson&amp;rsquo;s substack posts (Soon Parted ). Not because I disagree, but because I find Daniel&amp;rsquo;s blog informative, but lacking an MMT lens. But he gets a lot right, and is a student of Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s, so he understands balance sheets and whatnot. So with Daniel Nielson we are not dealing with some unhinged libertarian or Austrian School fantasist.</description></item><item><title>Proof of X</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_proof_of_x/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/11_proof_of_x/</guid><description>In casual talks with Douglas MMT Trader questions about what constitutes a &amp;ldquo;proof of MMT&amp;rdquo; or a disproof arose.
New Zealand is an MMT Economy We already know, from the Banking Acts and Public Finance Acts that New Zealand is an MMT monetary economy.
Just thought I&amp;rsquo;d mention this upfront. Although the legal statutes only prove half the case. We&amp;rsquo;d also need the accounting rules in the software and public accounts to obey the sectoral balance identities.</description></item><item><title>Source of Surplus Value</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_surplus_value/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/12_surplus_value/</guid><description>Even in Marx&amp;rsquo;s day &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; in social and relative utility terms, or any subjective terms that emerges in a society, was measured using the state&amp;rsquo;s unit of account (dollars, pounds, marks, yuan, yen, pesos, &amp;amp;c.)
So when some economist talks about theories of surplus value they often reduce to nominal terms (the state currency unit) not real terms (energy and material). But this is fine. As long as you know when it is appropriate to translate between real and nominal terms.</description></item><item><title>The Debt Pyramid or Stack</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_debt_pyramid/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/13_debt_pyramid/</guid><description>It is very painful listening to Perry Mehrling&amp;rsquo;s MOOC on Money and Banking.
Today the pain concerns the so-called money pyramid.
Money is Credit &amp;mdash; there is no pyramid&amp;hellip; Also all money is debt because credit is a promise to be redeemed, so is the debt of the issuer.
All money is an IOU of the issuer, the problem is getting others to accept it. However, a &amp;ldquo;money thing&amp;rdquo; (an IOU) is as good as gold if the issuer always backs up their promise to redeem.</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec2-5</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_1_mab3_4_civilwar/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-2 Money is Not Gold Mehrling thinks gold is money. This is nuts. He is terribly wrong, since a speck of gold dust is not a promise to redeem, nor a claim on anything.
Of course you can argue semantics: &amp;ldquo;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m defining gold dust as a &amp;lsquo;money thing&amp;rsquo; so suck it!</description></item><item><title>Money and Banking Lec3-4</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_mab_2_5_gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/14_mab_2_5_gold/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making the odd note about Mehrling&amp;#39;s course . This week I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a few more segments from Lecture-3 Money is Still Not Gold Just wanted to make a note that in this lecture it finally makes sense why Mehrling is obsessed with gold.
It is because he has a strong history buff spirit about him.
It is really the first time in the MOOC series when gold becomes important.</description></item><item><title>Status is a Beyatch</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_status_bitches/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/15_status_bitches/</guid><description>Interesting conversation Bill Mitchell had with a Japanese economics &amp;ldquo;professor&amp;rdquo; (professes to know some economics).
I made a few notes, not too many.
Japan Slips in GDP/Per Capita Ranking &amp;mdash; so what? The professor harped on a bit about how Japan had a &amp;ldquo;lost decade&amp;rdquo;. Bill explained well that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see in Japan any real loss of output. Their population growth is stagnant, so their GDP growth rate will not be anything near to say Australia which has a faster growing population.</description></item><item><title>Media Whores</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_media_whores/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/16_media_whores/</guid><description>I furore broke out in the right-wing media space recently, with some right-wing guy named &amp;ldquo;Crowder&amp;rdquo; attacking a &amp;ldquo;Jewish last name&amp;rdquo; right-wing media host &amp;mdash; probably by the name of Shapiro I am guessing. Shapiro apparently was offering Crowder a $\$50$ million contract over 4 years, but which had payments reduced if YouTube banned Crowder or if Crowder lost advertisers.
So what apparently happened is Crowder goes on some rant explaining how the Jewish side of the right-wing media is in league with &amp;ldquo;Big tech&amp;rdquo; and is out to stiff humble young millionaires like Crowder from getting their natural rights to the ad funds and billionaire oligarchs who fund right-wing media.</description></item><item><title>True Populist</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_true_populism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/17_true_populism/</guid><description>Anyone enjoy the first season of True Detective ? The &amp;ldquo;true detectives&amp;rdquo;, Rust and Marty, were very flawed people, but were driven by an unshakeable desire to see justice done &amp;mdash; admittedly only on the &amp;ldquo;catch the bad guy&amp;rdquo; side it has to be said, not the &amp;ldquo;raise up the poor&amp;rdquo; side, but whatever. Griping entertainment with cinematic risk (à la Scorsese ).
This post I&amp;rsquo;m going to have a crack at writing about similar risk in politics.</description></item><item><title>Machines Can't Think to Work</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_machinescandothework/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/18_machinescandothework/</guid><description>I get a few AI topic recommendations on social media these days, more frequently than a year ago, probably because I&amp;rsquo;m working with Douglas Macro Trader on neural net systems for predicting financial indices. Douglas and I have diverging views on the broader technology of so-called &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; (if it is true intelligence it is not artificial in my view).
I could write this article on my T4GU blog too, but since there is some overlap with the macroeconomics I thought it might be of interest to readers of Ōhanga Pai.</description></item><item><title>MMArt Critics</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/19_mmtreviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/19_mmtreviews/</guid><description>Following on from the Questions chapter I wrote last week &amp;ldquo;MMT and the Periphery &amp;rdquo; commentary, I thought it might be useful to critically review the defences of MMT, from a hard core MMT perspective (that&amp;rsquo;s me). At least I think I am hard core. As in what Buttercup said to Bubbles . What I&amp;rsquo;d mean by that is taking a view that the Mosler MMT Base Case is in fact realizable in the real world.</description></item><item><title>Euroland Is Ponzi</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/20_europonzi/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/20_europonzi/</guid><description>I was re-watching the MMT Fiscal Sustainability Conference 2010 (which has an interesting back-story) and found a lot of gems I&amp;rsquo;d forgotten. Bill Mitchell is hilarious, in a good way.
It was one of Mosler&amp;rsquo;s though that got me thinking.
At one point Warren says the eurozone member nations are effectively in a ponzi position. That&amp;rsquo;s using a particular definition of &amp;ldquo;ponzi&amp;rdquo;, which in this case was &amp;ldquo;having to get money from someone else&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>The Output Chasm</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/21_outputchasm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/21_outputchasm/</guid><description>Last post I wrote about the way the euroland is ponzi, which came from Warren Mosler at the MMT Fiscal Sustainability Conference 2010 , but that also led me to Bill Mitchell&amp;#39;s incredibly powerful statements on the massive costs of unemployment. The latter is what I want to focus more on today. I think it&amp;rsquo;s the single most important topic in macroeconomics. And second only in political economy to the issue of lasting world peace.</description></item><item><title>Macro Platonification</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/22_macro_platonification/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/22_macro_platonification/</guid><description>Over on my physics website for Topological 4-Geon Theory (T4GU) I recently wrote about platonism (healthy for thinking) versus platonification (deadly for thinking, and for general living). I think that reference sentence just gave you a summary, so no need to feel compelled to read it, it is however background to this current blog post.
(BTW: I have more to write about the last topic, the Output Chasm , but it is a heavy topic, so took a break from it.</description></item><item><title>When to Discard the MMT Lens</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/23_mmtfornow/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/23_mmtfornow/</guid><description>In recent times (tackling libertarians and crypto shills on social media) it has become glaringly apparent in economics &amp;mdash; macroeconomics in particular &amp;mdash; there is a massive culture of hostility to science. However, it is subtle, so worth writing about today.
When Science is Unscientific No macroeconomists aim to be unscientific, at least I think not. They do not intend to be hostile to science.
Yet anyone can claim they are &amp;ldquo;being scientific&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; say by legitimately using data, or logic, or a model.</description></item><item><title>Stuff Too Nasty for Twitter</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/24_toonastytwit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/24_toonastytwit/</guid><description>Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been becoming more resigned to the fact posts to Mastodon, Diaspora and Twitter are more about cheering the gang rather than getting people to think of updating their brain-based Bayesian filter .${}^\ast$
With this in mind, I&amp;rsquo;m going to post a few things here that I feel would just make enemies on social media, more than friends. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s light-hearted, and just to let off steam. Putting these posts on the github is a minimal act of sharing for those who care for a laugh.</description></item><item><title>Stuff Conservatives Want</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/25_conservatives/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/25_conservatives/</guid><description>Realistic timestamp on this post, since it&amp;rsquo;s a short one commenting on a short twitter to and fro.
I don&amp;rsquo;t mind the smell of conservatives, and have many as friends.
Previous chapter Back to Posts Next post Stuff Too Nasty for Twitter TOC AGI Fear &amp; Loathing</description></item><item><title>Fear & Loathing in Los Vital</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/26_agi_fearandloathing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/26_agi_fearandloathing/</guid><description>Sometimes I criss-cross posts on philosophy of mind between the physics (over at T4GU ) and the Macroeconomics here at Ōhanga Pai. Lunchtime today I was watching a fresh episode of Machine Language Street Talk &amp;mdash; MLST does not directly help with the MMT DougBot project, but I consider it peripheral research that&amp;rsquo;s loosely justified (for the creative mind you see, I can&amp;rsquo;t just go full Copilot and chatGPT for MMT).</description></item><item><title>Statistical Knowing</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/27_statsknowing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/27_statsknowing/</guid><description>More criss-crossing with my philosophy of mind between the physics (over at T4GU ). Although I try to keep the economics implications stuff here at Ōhanga Pai, and the physics stuff over at T4GU, today I will hedge on where my readers go and point them here. Today is a special blog where I will start to record my staking of positions on what the recent artificial intelligence LLM models can and cannot do.</description></item><item><title>Justice and Knowing</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/28_justiceandknowing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/28_justiceandknowing/</guid><description>A few notes on the flurry of news media on AI technology and fears of new AI monopoly owners held by tech giants, or the same powers open source released for rogue actors and rogue states to exploit. Some of this commentary is good, some terrible.
The biggest tragedy is all the politicians and commentariate screaming bloody murder about &amp;ldquo;jobs&amp;rdquo; being taken away. They are utterly ignorant and have zero comprehension of MMT.</description></item><item><title>Mushrooms and University</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/29_mushrooms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/29_mushrooms/</guid><description>A few comments today on medicinal psilocybin use and research. But the university topic will go further, because we read in last weeks New Zealand capital city last surviving newspaper, The Dominion Post, that universities are being starved of funding, may need to fire thousands of staff, and cut back research. Thousands of staff is enormous for a small nation like New Zealand, not small fries.
Thanks to my good friend, you know who you are, for prompting me to post this one.</description></item><item><title>UBInterested</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/30_ubinterested/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/30_ubinterested/</guid><description>Recently &amp;ldquo;friendlies&amp;rdquo; were hosting UBI shills, stabbing us in the back and twisting the knife, so I had to write to defend MMT.
I am so bitter about this I cannot name names, because that would imply friendly banter. I have to attack the ideas. There is nothing friendly about UBI, the UBI is a direct frontal attack on the working class. I have to fight back for workers.
When I name names, like Jason Hickel, Steve Keen, or Michael Hudson, or Paul Krugman, or Richard Wolff, and have something against their ideas to say, I&amp;rsquo;m always doing it in a good faith friendly way.</description></item><item><title>Cyberpunked</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/31_cyberpunked/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/31_cyberpunked/</guid><description>Some lighter material today. I want to pump the youtuber Quinn’s Ideas who is a wonderful creator of scifi discourse content. I realize it is pretty hilarious that my blog which no one seems to read is desiring to pump a youtuber who needs no pumping (550K+ views not uncommon). But&amp;hellip; you know&amp;hellip; 500K people is a sniff of the number of eyeballs that should be watching decent indie content. If I can get just two people to subscribe to Quinn’s Ideas my work will be done for today.</description></item><item><title>Talk with Warren Mosler - I</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/32_warrenmosler1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/32_warrenmosler1/</guid><description>If we are going to create chatMMT for fun, we are going to need a decent corpus of writing from Warren Mosler. You can&amp;rsquo;t easily get the snappy one-liners otherwise.
A lot of the cool stuff from Mosler is in youtube interviews, so some audio-to-text transcribing efforts are needed? Unpaid internships anyone? (Excuse the crassness! Couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself.) At least Google tensorflow tools can do most of the work for us these days.</description></item><item><title>Talk with Warren Mosler - II</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/33_warrenmosler2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/33_warrenmosler2/</guid><description>Besides chatting about physics, the other reason Warren called me was to help me reply to @paddymccoll on twitter who asked me about constraints on banks during the Bretton-Woods era.
Now, I am no expert on Bretton-Woods, but had talked with Steven Grumbine on the podcast Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese about foreign exchange constraints and things like BRICS currency, and all that. That was only because Steve could not get Bill Mitchell or another actual expert on the phone that week.</description></item><item><title>Blockchain Redundacle</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/34_blockchainredundacle/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/34_blockchainredundacle/</guid><description>The book “Blockchain Radicals” by Joshua Dávali promised up-front to give lefties or &amp;ldquo;revolutionaries&amp;rdquo; some insights into the way tech ools could promote social system and political change.
Since the modern scam grift/ponzi of all time, cryptocurrency, is a loony-toons libertarian project, I have no good reason to read Dávila&amp;rsquo;s book. But it was recommended by MMT aware writer Brett Scott, so I figured I should give Dávila some slack. This is my review.</description></item><item><title>MMT N00bs</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/35_mmtnoobs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/35_mmtnoobs/</guid><description>Today just some speech bullet points for people who may find they&amp;rsquo;re the &amp;ldquo;MMT expert in the room&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; meaning just an ordinary person who happens to know about MMT. These are the sorts of things you might want to have tattooed across your arms.
Caveats In polite discourse I do not recommend using my language of &amp;ldquo;Welfare Dorks&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;UBI Dorks&amp;rdquo; so please substitute appropriate terminology. Ōhanga Pai has elements of an MMT activist manifesto, so I allow myself such playful and provocative language.</description></item><item><title>Is Tax Hygiene?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/36_taxhygiene/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/36_taxhygiene/</guid><description>Been reading the essays in Modern Monetary Theory: Key Insights, Leading Thinkers and so might make a few comments over the next weeks.
Overall The book is too boring. A lot of excess verbiage. But no matter, all the essays are worth reading, just some are real snoozers though.
Also, f$\ast\ast$k! MMT is sooo UK centric man! Can&amp;rsquo;t f$\ast\ast$ing apply anywhere else, oh&amp;hellip; maybe in the EU? ;-)
Is Tax a Hygiene factor?</description></item><item><title>SocMed Peer Reviews</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/37_socmedreviews/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/37_socmedreviews/</guid><description>Today&amp;rsquo;s blog title is a play on social science academia. What I&amp;rsquo;m really going to do is indulge in some reviews of a bit of Twitter banter. Unfortunately for the sake of time and limited resources (MMT joke, but serious) I&amp;rsquo;ll probably have to stick to giving some hot takes, but here at least I get to write more at length than in a tweet.
I do have a serious purpose though.</description></item><item><title>USA Holds Back</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/38_usa_holdingback/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/38_usa_holdingback/</guid><description>On the MMT MacroTrader livestream I often enjoy politely shocking a few friends by saying how much I love Americans. This does not extend to their government or organizations, particularly not the parasitic financial sector (the latter can just go away with no damage to the economy, with the exception of banks that are permitted to asses credit risk and run the payments layer). I love their land and their people.</description></item><item><title>Kant Hegel MMM?</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/39_kant_v_hegel_v_mmt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/39_kant_v_hegel_v_mmt/</guid><description>Life has been friggin&amp;rsquo; traumatic for me recently, so excuse the low rate of blog output. Today I&amp;rsquo;m noting down a few thoughts after listening to Grumbine&amp;rsquo;s recent guest, Carlos García Hernández, on a topic he names “Fiat Socialism” &amp;mdash; a bit of a Frankenstein phrase if you ask me, which is what I&amp;rsquo;ll begin with, before getting into more juicy bits.
Language Framing I might make this language framing section a new regular feature of all my posts.</description></item><item><title>Regrowth Not Degrowth</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/40_regrowth/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/40_regrowth/</guid><description>Comments on a recent Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese podcast : “Degrowth and MMT” with Christopher Olk and Colleen Schneider . This is from a big Macro&amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo;Cheese fan. They&amp;rsquo;ve got a great library of podcasts.
Regrowth is Based While I absolutely unconditionally love my RealProgressives colleagues, the Degrowth meme and language framing is incrediubly dumb. I say this even though Bill Mitchell uses it (ok, he&amp;rsquo;s not a genius).
Here were my comments on the youtube copy of the podcast (I refuse Facebook, so cannto comment on the original websites).</description></item><item><title>Political Will</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/41_politicalstomach/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 09:45:00 +1200</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/41_politicalstomach/</guid><description>Reading a piece by Dougald Lamont here: “The Great Deception” about 20th century Canadian fascist fake-socialist politics and Tommy Douglas. Pretty fascinating.
My comments? I&amp;rsquo;ll be brief.
When &amp;ldquo;Politics&amp;rdquo; Sickens Us When the word &amp;ldquo;socialism&amp;rdquo; gets associated with so-called &amp;ldquo;Christian socialism&amp;rdquo; (disguising fascism, they&amp;rsquo;re neither Christian nor socialists) you get that sick feeling in your gut about &amp;ldquo;all politics&amp;rdquo;. it&amp;rsquo;s hard to avoid. But you have to avoid it.
Yes, by nature, economics and politics are sickening in both academic profession sphere and practical sphere.</description></item><item><title>Israel/Palestine</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/42_israel_palestine/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 13:25:00 +1200</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/42_israel_palestine/</guid><description>Saturday fun &amp;hellip; for some &amp;mdash; listening to Jeffry Sachs go counter-paradigm on Israel/Palestine. I&amp;rsquo;m enjoying this channel “Dialogue Works” .
Caveats I am not professionally into foreign affair politics, but my late father, Murray Smith, was deeply concerned with politics his whole life, and I received a lot of wisdom. However, all the flaws in thinking here in writing are my own.
Two States is Possible? I&amp;rsquo;d say politically calling for a Two State solution is achievable &amp;mdash; at the political level.</description></item><item><title>Demystify Debt</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/43_demystify_debt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 10:04:35 +1200</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/43_demystify_debt/</guid><description>A few comments this week on Michael Hudson and Steve Keen ranting on the DemystifySci podcast (here) . A nice confluence of an offbeat youtube channels I occassionally watch and MMM (the framework formerly known as MMT ;-)
I posted comment sthere, but pretty sure they&amp;rsquo;ll get &amp;ldquo;cleaned&amp;rdquo; (deleted) by someone. However, DemystifySci often have some interesting content on Ai, biotech, and related. It&amp;rsquo;s not all loony tunes, even though sometimes it is.</description></item><item><title>SAT Redo</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/44_sat_redo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/44_sat_redo/</guid><description>These days I don&amp;rsquo;t get much free time to check out the math-sci youtubes, but every so often Veritasium or some other offers a click bait title I cannot resist. There was this on on the infamous SAT coin rolling problem. “The SAT Question Everyone Got Wrong” That&amp;rsquo;s intriguing because you know there&amp;rsquo;s a deeper story behind it than merely &amp;ldquo;it was just a hard problem&amp;rdquo;.
SAT Administration The issue that prompted this blog today is the almost throw-away remark Veritasium made near the end on the inability of the SAT to re-score all the tests, citing it&amp;rsquo;d cost too much money that &amp;ldquo;came out of the pockets of the test takers.</description></item><item><title>The Public Hubble</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/45_thepublichubble/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/45_thepublichubble/</guid><description>Lunchtime listening this week, Brian Greene chatting with Adam Reiss on cosmology.
Hubble Telescope is in the Public Commons At one point Riess mentions he decided to not rest on his laurels, and went back into research &amp;ldquo;using the Hubble telescope.&amp;rdquo;
I could not resist the urge to post a yt comment boosting MMT.
@55:00 as a macroeconomics justice advocate I have to boost this: Riess using the Hubble telescope. It&amp;rsquo;s a public resource, in the public commons.</description></item><item><title>The Illicit Implicit</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/46_implicitbias/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/46_implicitbias/</guid><description>To celebrate getting off Twitter yesterday, I posted this link to post.news and Substack .
The Article Came across this nice article on the problems with &amp;ldquo;Implicit Bias training&amp;rdquo;. Lesson and take-away: if you want a better workplace, do not do IBT, it is a waste of time. Instead try being actually empathetic yourself, it rubs off, and remove workplace barriers to minorities and people with disabilities or neurodivergences.
Sadly, I found particularly odious the Upwork example cited in the Aeon article.</description></item><item><title>Bond Econ Bro</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/47_bondeconbro/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/47_bondeconbro/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m using Substack - Ohanga Pai and Post.news now for social media. Ethics demanded migrating off Twitter for real this time.
The Parasitism This is a comment on Brian Romanchuk&amp;rsquo;s blogging on FED and Treasury bond policy. I see it as all gigantic parasitic financial sector activity, it should be eliminated entirely. With one caveat.
When central banks offer a risk free rate, I see it as nothing but, &amp;ldquo;basic income but only for people who already have money, in proportion to how much they already have.</description></item><item><title>Goldiblocks</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/48_goldiblocks/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/48_goldiblocks/</guid><description>An internet friend, Nadine, sent me a link to a recent interview with Michael Hudson. I appreciated. Actually it was only a reaction video to an interview with Hudson, “Michael Hudson Actually Caused All This!” However, Hudson often makes me cringe. He is MMT aware, and friendly-ish, but not a proper MMT expert. This makes for sound cringebites worth commenting upon briefly.
I just wanted to get a few things off my chest with these latest cringebites.</description></item><item><title>Debt Curve Balls</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/49_debtcurve/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/49_debtcurve/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m at it again with Michael Hudson (here) .
I guess he is doing a good job opening people&amp;rsquo;s eyes and ears. But I wish he&amp;rsquo;d not continue being so coarse. It&amp;rsquo;s ok to talk in nuanced terms, and not jar your audience all the time. But maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just my sensitive ears.
Exponential Growth He got me started about 10 minutes in to the interview This is one annoying thing, it always irritates.</description></item><item><title>Loony Hoons</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/50_loonytoons/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/50_loonytoons/</guid><description>LoonyToon time again in Aotearoa New Zealand. Unlike Dr Bill Mitchell, I can afford to be short and sweet.
The New Zealand Tory government (National + ACT party) have macroeconomics completely backwards. Not just roughly. Completely. The &amp;ldquo;finance&amp;rdquo; Minister Nicola Willis went on official record the other day in proclaiming the NZ Government is like a household. Or, the Government Budget is &amp;ldquo;Like a Household Budget&amp;rdquo;.
Every MMT&amp;rsquo;er around knows this is utterly insane, and even a few post-Keynesian dimly know.</description></item><item><title>Boyz and Gr1lz</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/51_boyz_and_grilz/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/51_boyz_and_grilz/</guid><description>Gender Gaps, Real and Imagined Came across this DW News episode &amp;mdash; “Why the political worldviews of young men and women are increasingly diverging” discussing geneder gaps. Worth listening to, but I had a couple of slight objections to some of the language framing.
Early on one of the guests mentions that the social issues are not only problems for just boys.
5:30 probably could stop here, since this is the issue.</description></item><item><title>Cold Wars, New Wars</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/52_coldwars_newwars/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/52_coldwars_newwars/</guid><description>I was listening to Katrina van den Hueval on one of Pascal&amp;rsquo;s recent episodes over at Neutrality Studies .
Katrina mentioned how today the world&amp;rsquo;s security against nuclear weapon deployment seems more precarious than during the Cold War. Although I have not dug deep into any statistics to validate the proposition, I tend to agree. But I had to post a comment:
@15:30 while it is probably true our times are more unstable than the Cold War era, this is good${}^\ddagger$.</description></item><item><title>Silo Tokens</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/53_silo_tokens/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/53_silo_tokens/</guid><description>When I&amp;rsquo;m tired or depressed and can&amp;rsquo;t function too well mathematically I tend to go for scifi. Action movies are so damn boring.
I had a peek at the series Silo .
That affords a chance to rant about use of gold tokens as currency. Same stupidity depicted in the Star Wars spin-off series Andor .
Why? I mean&amp;hellip; just&amp;hellip; why?
In an underground bunker silo with probably a hundred thousand citizens, why on Earth, or under Earth, would they use a physical gold token as currency?</description></item><item><title>Central Splanning</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/54_central_splanning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/54_central_splanning/</guid><description>How one thing leads to another, huh? After a long gap between Ōhanga Pai posts I have two in short succession. This one could turn out juicier, since it is a complex topic. The occasion is coming across a Santa Fe Institute public talk on central planning: “Comrades, Let&amp;amp;rsquo;s Optimize! The Surprising Rebirth of the Planned Economy” at SFI, March 10. The guest speaker was Francis Spufford who wrote a book called “Red Plenty” Setting the Scene I am pretty sure Spufford is getting a lot of things wrong.</description></item><item><title>Total Value Recall</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/55_total_value/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/55_total_value/</guid><description>A nice change-up from recent posts today, I get to comment on Randall Wray&amp;rsquo;s chat with Grumbine, Defining Value with L. Randall Wray on Real Progressives, March 10 2024.
How could I possibly add any value to what Wray has to say on use of a monetary unit to communicate economic value? Amazingly there was a door Wray left slightly open.
Labour Theory of Value is Not Total Value Wray does a nice job summarizing Marx, and not in the Monty Python Proust way, although that would have been cool too.</description></item><item><title>Media Mirrors</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/56_media_mirrors/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/blog/56_media_mirrors/</guid><description>Here is an interesting discussion with Pascal Lottaz from Neutrality Studies with a sociologist, Dr. Harald Welzer, and a data scientist, Leo Keller, who collaborated to study the difference between official published accounts and public opinion. No surprises official accounts diverge from public opinion. this could be good and bad. Public opinion can be false, or public opinion gained through informal social communication unfiltered by mainstream media can in some cases be more accurate.</description></item></channel></rss>