<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Overview</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</guid><description>Overview of the Projects Asset Exchange Models These are pretty simple models in the class of &amp;ldquo;econophysics&amp;rdquo;. They are agent-based models, and show the basic wealth distributions that occur generically given some rules for how entities (individuals or units like small firms) exchange assets.
These models are great for thinking about fair distribution policies, which at a government regulatory level means fiscal policy. The models show that highly unfair wealth distributions naturally occur even when asset exchanges are uniform and random.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/0_introduction_to_projects/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/empirical/0_introduction_to_projects/</guid><description>This section is for discussions (in article form) of theory and empirical research development.
Contributors are welcome, but will need to submit through the Contact form. Your article needs to be technical, not philosophical.
The philosophy and questions section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for the Ōhanga Pai community.
This section of articles gives you just a little taste of some projects I might be working on, time and willing collaborators permitting.</description></item></channel></rss>