<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/000_empirical_intro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/000_empirical_intro/</guid><description>This section is for discussions (in article form) of theory and empirical research development.
Contributors are welcome, but will need to submit through the Contact form or email. Your article needs to be technical, not philosophical, with ideally a code contribution to the github repository.
The philosophy and questions section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for the Ōhanga Pai community.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Overview</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/001_ohangapai_projects/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/001_ohangapai_projects/</guid><description>Overview of the Projects Asset Exchange Models These are pretty simple models in the class of &amp;ldquo;econophysics &amp;rdquo;. They are agent-based models, and show the basic wealth distributions that occur generically given some rules for how entities (individuals or units like small firms) exchange assets.
These models are great for thinking about fair distribution policies, which at a government regulatory level means fiscal policy. The models show that highly unfair wealth distributions naturally occur even when asset exchanges are uniform and random.</description></item><item><title>Minsky Model Batch Jobs</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/002_minskybasics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/002_minskybasics/</guid><description>TODO: incomplete. Could not actually get minsky running on the cmdl. REST API was not working. We are working on artificial neural net models for S&amp;amp;P500 time series forecasting, but before all that research is released I wanted to give the community some tips and tricks for using the system dynamics software Minksy™, which is Steve Keen and hpcoder&amp;rsquo;s project, you can get open source releases on sourceforge here.
Sine this is the first post on Minksy-SD, I will begin with a minimal set-up introduction.</description></item><item><title>Macro Trading 1 - Intro</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/099_1_macro_trader/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/099_1_macro_trader/</guid><description>Macro trading is something I&amp;rsquo;ve only recently looked into, not as a trader, but as an academic seeking more real world experience. Macro trading models can benefit from MMT, but do not really use a bare Keen&amp;ndash;Minksy model because of the need to model markets, which are sub-macro. So I place macro trading models in a category of mesoscopic MMT analysis.
The MMT Macro Trader Paradigm Douglas over at Doug - MMT Macro Trader does a terrific job of using Bayesian models and MMT fiscal flow analysis to get very, very good 30 day predictions for the S&amp;amp;P forward market.</description></item><item><title>MT-2 - Flow of Funds</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/099_2_funds_flows/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/099_2_funds_flows/</guid><description>The second in the planned series on Macro Trading MMT (MT for short.)
Sectoral Balances for Trading Alan Longbon wrote an interesting article on SeekingAlpha which outlined his investment strategy, which is pretty simple and highly MMT informed.
&amp;ldquo;My investment approach is very simple. I find countries with the highest and strongest macro-fiscal flows and low levels of private debt and invest in them using country ETFs and contract for difference (CFDs)I use functional finance and sectoral flow analysis of the national accounts of the nations I invest in.</description></item><item><title>NZ Macroconomics — I</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/100_nzecon_i/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/100_nzecon_i/</guid><description>A new series on some aspects of NZ macroeconomics. Topics are just whatever I bother to look at and write-up. Today, the Real NZ government surplus(deficit).
NZ Government Real Deficit This is topical whenever there is a significant inflation event, and such has occurred post-COVID.
We need a formula that can show how a nominal deficit can become a real surplus from the non-government sector&amp;rsquo;s perspective when inflation is high enough.</description></item><item><title>Macromodels I --- Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/300_1_macromodels_intro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/300_1_macromodels_intro/</guid><description>This is a new chapter series on macroeconomic modelling. I set my task to go through all the crud before getting to the good stuff of MMT and Minsky/GodleyTable models. The desire would be to do as much justice to the lamestream models, and then test them against empirical data.
The two mainstream models will be,
IS-LM DSGE. That&amp;rsquo;s the crud.
Then we will try to increase sophistication:
CNN/LSTM fit models (to provide a base case for prevailing policy conditions).</description></item><item><title>Macromodels II --- IS-LM</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/301_2_macromodels_islm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/301_2_macromodels_islm/</guid><description>IS-LM History This is the original bastardization of Keynes&amp;rsquo; General Theory. It was invented by John Hicks. It was always a stupid toy model. The fact professional academic economists still teach this model is weird. It is not like teaching Newtonian Gravity for physics classes, it is far worse. That is because there is Zero Knowledge in the IS-LM model. It does not begin with correct assumptions. Newtonian Gravity at least begins (albeit only in hindsight) with a very good approximation to GR.</description></item><item><title>Macromodels III --- IS-LM</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/302_3_macromodels_islm_2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/302_3_macromodels_islm_2/</guid><description>Things get a bit messy now. If you inspect the code for our OpenEconomyISLMModel class in the python module, you will see we&amp;rsquo;ve added a time series analysis class TimeSeriesISLMModel which will help us run some quasi-predictive tests against real world data.
Recall by &amp;ldquo;quasi-predictive&amp;rdquo; we run immediately into troubles since IS-LM is a static equilibrium model. The idea of bastardizing Keynes&amp;rsquo; General Theory is to at least pay a little bit of homage to Keynes and try to make the ISLM model a moving equilibria (whatever that means!</description></item><item><title>Macromodels IV --- IS-LM, part-3</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/303_4_macromodels_islm_3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/303_4_macromodels_islm_3/</guid><description>I will try to use &amp;lsquo;ISLM&amp;rsquo; for the general idea of ISLM modelling, I will use lowercase &amp;lsquo;islm&amp;rsquo; for our particular python model, which I&amp;rsquo;ve also named OpenEconomyISLMModel().
ISLM Scenario Testing Basically we want to know for what the model can predict, how good is it? An AIC score might be nice too.
The problem with ISLM is that it is not fit for forecasting. What it portends to accomplish is take an existing set of macroeconomic variables, suppose some of them change in the future, and then output $Y$ and interest rate $r$ are predicted for a new equilibrium.</description></item><item><title>Macromodels V --- DSGE</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/310_1_macromodels_dsge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/310_1_macromodels_dsge/</guid><description>Beyond IS-LM We already mentioned the DSGE model, which we will discuss in a later chapter.
There is another more minimal extension of IS-LM, the AD-AS model (Aggregate Demand&amp;ndash;Aggregate Supply) but it does not significantly patch any of the flaws in IS-LM, so is still a Zero Informative model. We will instead, after briefly looking at DSGE, jump to a more MMT-like model due to the economist Dirk Ehnts &amp;mdash; the so-called ISMY model.</description></item><item><title>Macromodels VI --- ISMY</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/320_1_macromodels_ismy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/320_1_macromodels_ismy/</guid><description> Previous chapter Back to Next chapter MM—V, DSGE TOC MM—VII, Levey</description></item><item><title>Macromodels VII --- Levey</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/330_1_macromodels_levey/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/330_1_macromodels_levey/</guid><description> Previous chapter Back to Next chapter MM—VI, ISMY TOC MM—VIII, Minksy</description></item><item><title>Macromodels VIII --- Minsky</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/340_1_macromodels_minsky/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/340_1_macromodels_minsky/</guid><description> Previous chapter Back to Next chapter MM—VII, Levey TOC MM—IX, CNN-LSTM</description></item><item><title>Macromodels IX --- CNN-LSTM</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/350_1_macromodels_lstm/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/350_1_macromodels_lstm/</guid><description> Previous chapter Back to Next chapter MM—VIII, Minsky TOC MM—X, SINDy</description></item><item><title>Quantopian Series Notes</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</guid><description>A few highlights from the Quantopian Series worth remembering for teaching. these will start off unordered, but after I write a half dozen or so I will try to impose some loose pedagogical order. (That just means the links will change, ok. So if referencing use the TOC and search box instead.)
p-value Hacking Ref: Quantopian Lecture Series: p-Hacking and Multiple Comparisons Bias .
Terminology False positive &amp;mdash; a test indicates presence of an effect when in reality an oracle would say there is no effect.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/romanchuk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/romanchuk/</guid><description>Suppose the central bank sets interest rates according to the following rule.
i_t=\sigma \pi_t +\theta,
where \pi is inflation, i_t is the nominal interest rate, and \theta is a AR(1) error term with mean zero. \sigma is a parameter that governs how strongly the central bank responds to inflation.
The Euler equation gives us the following expression
Y_t=E(Y_t)-(i_t-E(\pi_{t+1})),
which gives us i_t=E(\pi_{t+1}) if Y_t is constant. Combining the two expressions we get</description></item></channel></rss>