<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ōhanga Pai</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/</link><description>Geon Theory Development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2022, Bijou Murray Smith; All rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quantopian Series Notes</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/999_1_quantopian_phacks/</guid><description>A few highlights from the Quantopian Series worth remembering for teaching. these will start off unordered, but after I write a half dozen or so I will try to impose some loose pedagogical order. (That just means the links will change, ok. So if referencing use the TOC and search box instead.)
p-value Hacking Ref: Quantopian Lecture Series: p-Hacking and Multiple Comparisons Bias .
Terminology False positive &amp;mdash; a test indicates presence of an effect when in reality an oracle would say there is no effect.</description></item><item><title>MT-2 - Flow of Funds</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_2_funds_flows/</guid><description>The second in the planned series on Macro Trading MMT (MT for short.)
Sectoral Balances for Trading Alan Longbon wrote an interesting article on SeekingAlpha which outlined his investment strategy, which is pretty simple and highly MMT informed.
&amp;ldquo;My investment approach is very simple. I find countries with the highest and strongest macro-fiscal flows and low levels of private debt and invest in them using country ETFs and contract for difference (CFDs)I use functional finance and sectoral flow analysis of the national accounts of the nations I invest in.</description></item><item><title>Macro Trading 1 - Intro</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/99_1_macro_trader/</guid><description>Macro trading is something I&amp;rsquo;ve only recently looked into, not as a trader, but as an academic seeking more real world experience. Macro trading models can benefit from MMT, but do not really use a bare Keen&amp;ndash;Minksy model because of the need to model markets, which are sub-macro. So I place macro trading models in a category of mesoscopic MMT analysis.
The MMT Macro Trader Paradigm Douglas over at Doug - MMT Macro Trader does a terrific job of using Bayesian models and MMT fiscal flow analysis to get very, very good 30 day predictions for the S&amp;amp;P forward market.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Overview</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/1_ohangapai_projects/</guid><description>Overview of the Projects Asset Exchange Models These are pretty simple models in the class of &amp;ldquo;econophysics &amp;rdquo;. They are agent-based models, and show the basic wealth distributions that occur generically given some rules for how entities (individuals or units like small firms) exchange assets.
These models are great for thinking about fair distribution policies, which at a government regulatory level means fiscal policy. The models show that highly unfair wealth distributions naturally occur even when asset exchanges are uniform and random.</description></item><item><title>Ōhanga Pai Projects Introduction</title><link>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/00_empirical_intro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://smithwillsuffice.github.io/ohanga-pai/empirical/00_empirical_intro/</guid><description>This section is for discussions (in article form) of theory and empirical research development.
Contributors are welcome, but will need to submit through the Contact form or email. Your article needs to be technical, not philosophical, with ideally a code contribution to the github repository.
The philosophy and questions section of this website goes through in a breezy way some of the concepts and possible avenues of research for the Ōhanga Pai community.</description></item></channel></rss>